<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Prelimited forms of praising God, vocally sung by all the church together, proved to be no gospel ordinance. In a sober discourse concerning singing. With a large appendix thereunto added, containing several things not treated of before; and wherein the case of singing is more fully opened and discussed in divers principal branches of it: greatly tending to the clearing and confirmation of the truth discoursed of in the former part. / By Isaac Marlow.</title>
            <author>Marlow, Isaac.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1691</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 195 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 65 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B04474</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing M693A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R233424</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">52614784</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 52614784</idno>
            <idno type="VID">175970</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B04474)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 175970)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English Books, 1641-1700 ; 2757:11)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Prelimited forms of praising God, vocally sung by all the church together, proved to be no gospel ordinance. In a sober discourse concerning singing. With a large appendix thereunto added, containing several things not treated of before; and wherein the case of singing is more fully opened and discussed in divers principal branches of it: greatly tending to the clearing and confirmation of the truth discoursed of in the former part. / By Isaac Marlow.</title>
                  <author>Marlow, Isaac.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>23, 50, [2], 48 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for the author,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1691.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"Brief discourse concerning singing" has special t.p. and separate pagination. "Appendix to the former discourse" has separate pagination.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: print show-through with loss of text.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: National Library of Scotland.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Music in churches --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Psalmody --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Singing --  Religious aspects --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:175970:1"/>
            <p>PRELIMITED FORMS of Praiſing GOD, Vocally ſung by all the Church together, Proved to be no Goſpel-Ordinance.</p>
            <p>In a Sober Diſcourſe concerning SINGING.</p>
            <p>With a Large APPENDIX Thereunto added, Containing ſeveral Things not treat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of before; and wherein the Caſe of SINGING is more fully opened and diſcuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in divers principal Branches of it: Greatly tending to the clearing and confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of the Truth diſcourſed of in the Former Part.</p>
            <p>By <hi>ISAAC MARLOW.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>1 Sam. 15.22.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Behold, to obey is better than Sacrifice; and to hearken, than the Fat of Rams.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for the Author, 1691.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:175970:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:175970:2"/>
            <head>THE EPISTLE DEDICATORY TO THE Baptized Churches Of Chriſt in <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Wales.</hi>
            </head>
            <head type="sub">Grace, Mercy and Peace be multiplied unto you, from God our Father, and Jeſus Chriſt our Saviour.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Honoured and Beloved Brethren,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>AS the ſubject Matter of the fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing Diſcourſe is in defence of the true Apoſtolical Scripture manner of Divine Service, and of the Spiritual Worſhip of God, which you have owned and ſuffered for, and in which thrô the Grace of Chriſt you ſtill continue, and as it tends to the mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Peace and Unity of the Churches; ſo I hope that my Work and Service herein will find the greater acceptance with you.</p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:175970:3"/>
            <p>And ſeeing it hath graciouſly plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed God to preſerve you ſo ſtedfaſtly in the Truth under the greateſt Trials and Sufferings of our Age, it is to be ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped that the Errors of ſome Perſons ſhall never corrupt your Minds from the Simplicity that is in Chriſt, in any part of Divine Worſhip, or to offer your Praiſes to God in ſuch humane Forms, and after ſuch a manner, as we have no example for, nor can be any ways warranted from the Word of God: And that thoſe Churches which have had a watchful eye againſt the fineſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpun Errors of their Day, will not be now lull'd aſleep by any among them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, to ſuffer the bringing in of ſuch a humane Tradition as is utterly incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtent with their profeſſed Principles, and to their Practice in other parts of Divine Worſhip; but that they will labour to have Oil in their Veſſels with their Lamps, that ſo when the Bride<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>groom cometh, they may be ready to enter into the Joy of their Lord. For though this Error is dearly fondled by ſome Chriſtians, and as it is obſerved moſtly by ſuch among us who have not well digeſted thoſe things which they
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:175970:3"/>have received; yet of about an hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred Churches in <hi>England,</hi> according to the beſt and ſtricteſt Information I have received, I hear of but ſeven or eight, and thoſe are in and about <hi>Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>folk, Suffolk</hi> and <hi>Eſſex,</hi> one of them lately in <hi>London,</hi> and but four or five of all thoſe Churches in <hi>South-Wales,</hi> which own the Doctrine of Perſonal Election and final Perſeverance; and but two of all thoſe Churches that are for the general Point that practiſe ſuch formal Singing in the publick and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Worſhip of God with the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry of the Word. Some few alſo there are that uſe it at the Adminiſtration of the Lord's Supper: To whom and to all others in particular of my Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Brethren, that herein differ from the Body of the Churches, and are decli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning from the Truth and Spirituality of Goſpel-Worſhip, I humbly preſent that which the Lord hath convinced me of through the Light of the Holy Scriptures, to remove the Miſtake you are under concerning Singing. And truly the Senſe I have of the ſad Ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects of this apoſtatizing Principle in ſome Chriſtians, if it ſhould grow and
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:175970:4"/>increaſe among us, and the unwearied Endeavours of ſome Perſons to lead us back to ſuch Traditions of Men from which we were clean eſcaped, with the Love I have for the Truth and Sim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicity of the Goſpel, are the only Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives of my appearing in this Work or Service.</p>
            <p>And it is matter of Grief and La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentation to many Chriſtians, that while the Lord is ſaving his Church and People, and is drawing of us with the gracious Cords of his Love, that any ſhould be departing from the Truth and Purity of his Worſhip, which af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſo clear a light and recovery of it from the miſts and darkneſs of Men, is now called in queſtion amongſt our ſelves.</p>
            <p>And it is ſomewhat marvellous to conſider, that ſome Perſons who are ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious and underſtanding in the Holy Scriptures, ſhould not ſee their Practice to be oppoſite to the poſitive Command of Jeſus Chriſt, through whoſe know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg others that are weak are made to ſin. And that any ſhould be ſo cold in their Love and Affections to Chriſt, and ſo indifferent in their Obedience
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:175970:4"/>unto his revealed Will, as that they ſhould rather truſt to others for what is truth, than to take the pains to ſearch the Scriptures for ſatisfaction from a good Underſtanding within themſelves, whereby they follow the Dictates of Men more than the Precepts of Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
            <p>But foraſmuch as humane Forms of Worſhip do naturally proceed from a carnal and worldly Spirit, we may then fear that ſome Chriſtians (ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepting others that err through a miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taken Zeal) having left their firſt Love, begin to caſt off their firſt Faith, and to turn unto Mens Traditions, of whom and to whom, we may ſay, as the Apoſtle did to thoſe who were turning again to the weak and beggar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Elements of the Law, <hi>O fooliſh</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.1, 3, 4.</note> Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latians, <hi>who hath bewitched you, that you ſhould not obey the truth? — Are ye ſo fooliſh, having begun in the Spirit, are ye now made perfect by the Fleſh? Have ye ſuffered ſo many things in vain, if it be yet in vain?</hi> And is it a ſmall and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different thing with you, how and in what manner you worſhip God, and offer your Praiſe unto him? Have ye
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:175970:5"/>not as much reaſon to obſerve the Rule of Chriſt in praiſing, and giving Thanks, as well as in Prayer, Baptiſm, and other Ordinances in the Church? If any ſhould tell you, that becauſe Prayer and Baptiſm are commanded by Jeſus Chriſt, therefore you muſt uſe Forms of Prayer, and Infants-ſprinkling, will you not ſay to them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, That the Concluſion is not ratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal? For though theſe are commanded, yet the manner how theſe Ordinances are to be performed, whether in and through the Gifts and Graces of the Holy Spirit, and by dipping, or by hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane precompoſed Forms, and ſprink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, is not left to our own Wills, but are alſo ſhewed to us in the holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, which are the Rule for the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of performance of all the eſſential Parts of Goſpel-Worſhip. And if any ſhould further ſay, that Infants ſprink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling is not expreſly forbidden in the Scriptures, and therefore it may be u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by us: will you not make reply, that though it is not forbidden in ſuch expreſs words, yet there being but one manner of Water-Baptiſm commanded by Chriſt and his holy Apoſtles, whoſe
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:175970:5"/>Precepts and Examples therein we are bound to follow, it is a ſufficient War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant for our practice of it, and to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude the form of Sprinkling as a ſinful Practice, in that it changeth the Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, and maketh void the Command of Chriſt, through Mens Traditions? And therefore if you will not reject your Manner and Forms of Singing, from the obſervation of the Command and Rule of Chriſt for the manner of Praiſing God, which is contrary to your Manner and Forms, I ſee not how you can eſcape the battering and confound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of your own Profeſſion in other things.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Do ye provoke the Lord to jealouſy?</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.22.</note> 
               <hi>are ye ſtronger than he?</hi> Hath he not ſaid, <hi>What things ſoever I command you,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Deut.</hi> 12.32.</note> 
               <hi>obſerve to do it: thou ſhalt not add there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, nor diminiſh from it?</hi> And have we not divers inſtances of his ſore Diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure for breaking his Rule of Worſhip, as in <hi>Nahab</hi> and <hi>Abihu,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Lev.</hi> 7.11, to 19.</note> who for offering of ſtrange Fire, died before the Lord? And might not ſome have thought it a ſmall matter to have eaten of the Peace or Thank-offering after the Firſt-day, or of the Vow-offering, if any of it
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:175970:6"/>had been left on the Third-day? but we ſee how great an Offence it was to make ſo ſmall an Addition to God's Ordinance, as that it ſhould not be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted, neither ſhould it be imputed unto him that offereth it: it ſhould be an Abomination, and that Soul ſhould bear his Iniquity.<note place="margin">2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 6.6.</note> Moreover, We read how <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>zzah</hi> loſt his Life for touching the Ark of God, becauſe that they ſought him not after the due order; and how <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>zziah</hi> the King for med<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling with God's Ordinance,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 26.16. 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 15.13.</note> and burn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Incenſe before the Lord, contrary unto his revealed Will, was ſmote with Leproſy unto his dying Day. But notwithſtanding theſe <hi>Old Teſtament</hi> Examples, and the Word of Chriſt which ſaith, <hi>In vain do they worſhip me, teaching for Doctrines the Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of Men;</hi> yet ſome there are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt us, that dare adventure to break the Commands of Chriſt in their Vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal-ſinging together in the Worſhip of God, contrary to the Rule of Worſhip and Inſtitution of Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
            <p>And therefore, ſeeing that their Practice is charged with the guilt of Sin; yea, and of ſuch a Sin as indan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:175970:6"/>the well-Being and Peace of the Church of Chriſt, and the bringing of God's Diſpleaſure upon us: I hope they will be awakned to a ſerious Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration of what is propoſed to them herein, as the Mind and Will of God: And ſurely if they were truly ſenſible of the natural Conſequences of ſuch a Practice of formal Singing, that the introducing of it into thoſe Churches that have been eſtabliſhed on contrary Principles, is the ready way to divide and break them into pieces, and that thoſe Perſons who ſhould be inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental therein, would be looked upon as the Troublers of the Churches, and may be juſtly charged with Schiſm, it would be a Bar to their zealous promo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of it.</p>
            <p>And it is rational to believe, that if ſuch formal Singing ſhould be admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and imbraced by the Churches, it would lay ſuch a Foundation for other formal and carnal Worſhip, that if it be followed in its natural Tendences and Conſequences, it will greatly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>danger our reformed Separation, and make it eaſy for us to glide into the National Way of Worſhip. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:175970:7"/>whatever our miſtaken Brethren may think of themſelves, as if they were reforming the Goſpel-Church, and reſtoring the Primitive Worſhip of God therein; yet the holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures witneſs againſt them, and I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve that they will be found in this matter Leaders to Apoſtacy, and Defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers of the pure Worſhip of God with Mens Traditions: Which that the Lord may graciouſly prevent, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve the Churches in Peace and Union, and in the mutual fellowſhip of the Goſpel, and that they may flouriſh and grow in Grace, and in the Knowledg of Jeſus Chriſt, and become a great Mountain, and fill the Face of the whole Earth, is, and ſhall be, the Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of your unworthy, but affectionate Brother and Servant to his power, in Jeſus Chriſt our Lord.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>I. M.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:175970:7"/>
            <head>THE <hi>Author's EPISTLE</hi> TO <hi>Mr.</hi> Benjamin Keach.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Chriſtian Brother.</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>AS the holy Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> praiſed the Church of <hi>Corinth</hi> in all things ſo far as they kept the Ordinances of Chriſt as they were deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered to them, and yet faithfully re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved their diſorderly manner of eating the Lord's Supper;<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.2, 17.</note> ſo in imitation of him, as our Example, I commend you in thoſe things wherein you are praiſe-wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy, and do honour you for your labour in the Miniſtry of the Word which God has been pleaſed to bleſs, to the awak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of many Souls, and to the comfort of many Chriſtians: But yet, Sir, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing you have divers ways (I think I may
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:175970:8"/>ſafely ſay) ſingled forth your ſelf more than others in <hi>London,</hi> in puſhing for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward the Practice of formal Singing, and in your private and publick Challen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of Diſputes, which have been divers times accepted of by ſome of our worthy Elders, but were never thought conveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent by others, and ſo have been laid aſide; and in that you have lately brought in the practice of it into your own Church, to the grief and trouble of many of your Members; I conceive that it is not im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proper for me to acquaint you in this manner, That I think I am divers ways engaged, and do believe it is my Duty to imploy the Talent which God hath gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven me, according to my Capacity, in the defence of his ſacred Truth, againſt that miſchievous Error which you ſo vigo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rouſly promote, to the diſturbance of your Brethren. Have not you been for many years a Preacher up of ſpiritual Worſhip? how is it then that you are now ſo zealous for that which is aſſerted to be natural? Have you begun in the Spirit, and do you leave the Principles of the Doctrine of Chriſt to go on unto perfection in na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Worſhip? On what Foundation does your Practice ſtand? We do all agree
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:175970:8"/>that it is our Duty to praiſe and thank God as well as to pray unto him; and I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve that you will not ſay but that we do thank and praiſe him in his Worſhip, thô not with Songs in your way. And I am perſwaded that our thanking and praiſing God in Prayer or Prayer-wiſe is ſuitable to the other ordinary Gifts of the Holy Spirit, which are only attained unto in our preſent Day, and is proportionably ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted of God: and that as your manner of vocal ſinging together hath neither Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Command nor Example for it in ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Old or the New Teſtaments, ſo your ſinging of formal precompoſed ſtinted matter is no better than counterfeitiag that excellent Gift of the Holy Spirit which was in the Primitive Goſpel-Church. And herein alſo I believe that we do not differ, That by the Light of Nature the Eternal Power and Godhead is made ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifest unto us from the things that do ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear; and that we are capable thereby to underſtand that we ſhould perfectly keep the Law of God, and praiſe and worſhip him. But from hence ariſeth a double Queſtion.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <hi>1.</hi> Whether the Light of Nature it ſelf, as it is in us, can direct us <hi>the Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:175970:9"/>how we ſhould worſhip God,</hi> and whether we ſhould rely on it under the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel as our Rule of Worſhip?</p>
            <p n="2">
               <hi>2.</hi> Whether you will aſſert that meerly natural Worſhip without Goſpel-Inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and Qualifications (for that which is Legal and Ceremonial is done away) will pleaſe God, and ought to be exerciſed in his Goſpel-Church? Or,</p>
            <p n="3">
               <hi>3.</hi> Do you ſay that the acceptable man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of praiſing God in his Goſpel-Church (for that is the chiefeſt Point in queſtion) is diſcovered and warranted to us both from the Light of Nature, and Divine Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations and Goſpel-Inſtitutions; and ſo becauſe you have no Warrant from either of them for your Practice of formal Sing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing together, do you ſhuffle between them both? If you ſay, that your Practice of ſinging Praiſes to God in his Church, is a conſtant Ordinance by Divine Revelation and Inſtitution only; then you cannot pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to the Practice of it from the Law or Inſtinct of Nature: and if you found it on the Law of Nature only; then you bring it into the Goſpel-Church, without regard being had to the Tenor of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel, which is, that as <hi>God is a Spirit,</hi> ſo <hi>they that worſhip him muſt worſhip
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:175970:9"/>in Spirit and in Truth:</hi> as Chriſt ſaith, <hi>The Hour cometh and now is,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Joh.</hi> 4.23, 24.</note> 
               <hi>when the true Worſhippers ſhall worſhip the Father in Spirit and in Truth: for the Father ſeeketh ſuch to worſhip him.</hi> Which is not to be underſtood of worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping in our natural Spirits only: For the Apoſtle ſaith,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.8, 26, 27.</note> that <hi>they that are in the Fleſh, cannot pleaſe God. But ye are not in the Fleſh, but in the Spirit, if ſo be that the Spirit of God dwell in you. Now if any Man have not the Spirit of Chriſt, he is none of his.</hi> And that <hi>the Spirit alſo helpeth our Infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties: for we know not what we ſhould pray for as we ought: but the Spirit it ſelf maketh interceſſion for us with Groanings which cannot be uttered.</hi> And we are commanded to <hi>pray always with all Prayer and Supplication in the Spirit:</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 6.18</note> And to <hi>pray in the Holy Ghoſt;</hi> and to <hi>be filled with the Spirit:</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Chap.</hi> 5.18, 19.</note> 
               <hi>ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to your ſelves in Pſalms, and Hymns, and Spiritual Songs.</hi> And <hi>I will pray with the Spirit:</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.15.</note> and <hi>I will ſing with the Spirit.</hi> And the Apoſtle ſaith in his Epiſtles to the <hi>Romans</hi> and <hi>Galatians;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.15.</note> 
               <hi>Becauſe ye are Sons, God hath ſent forth the Spirit of his Son into your
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:175970:10"/>Hearts, crying, Abba, Father.</hi> And <hi>ye have received the Spirit of Adoption,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.6.</note> 
               <hi>whereby we cry, Abba, Father.</hi> So that Goſpel-Prayer and Singing is <hi>in, with,</hi> and <hi>by</hi> the help of the Holy Spirit. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore if no regard be had to Goſpel-Inſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and Qualifications for Prayer &amp; Sing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, but that they are to be practiſed from the Law, Light, or Inſtinct of Nature only; then ſuch Prayer and Singing, ſo perform'd, can't be part of Goſpel-Worſhip; nor ſhould they be knowingly ſuffered in any Goſpel-Church. For the deſign of God in erect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Goſpel-Church was, that he might have <hi>a Spiritual Houſe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.5, 9.</note> 
               <hi>an Holy Prieſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood, to offer up ſpiritual</hi> (not natural) <hi>Sacrifices, acceptable to God by Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> Moreover, if Singing and Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er are put together, and performed by you as ſpiritual Duties, why do you not follow the ſpiritual Rule and plain Goſpel-Order for Singing as well as Prayer? And if you put them together as natural Duties from the Law or Inſtinct of Nature only, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out regard being had to Divine Inſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and Qualifications, it is the ready way to bring the World by Shoals into the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel-Church, and ſo to turn it by major Votes, which is no argument of Truth,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:175970:10"/>into a natural Church-ſtate. And it alſo opens a wide door for Forms of Prayer, as well as for Forms of Singing: for if the Practice of both are alike from the Law of Nature, and Singing be performed in ſtinted precompoſed Forms; what reaſon can you render, why ſuch Forms of Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er ſhould not be uſed as well as ſuch Forms of Singing? But if Singing and Prayer are not put together by you, as founded alike on the Law of Nature; how can you de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrate their Eſſences to be from the different Principles of Nature and Grace, when true Goſpel ſpiritual Singing is from the Fountain of the Holy Spirit, as well as Prayer; and preſerve the Goſpel-Church from the Confuſion of apparently-known natural and ſpiritual Perſons, in having full Communion together, if natural Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, meerly as ſuch, ſhould be allowed therein? Farthermore, what Scripture-Grounds and Reaſons can you render (when you perform Prayer according to Goſpel-Order in the Church, with a ſingle Voice, by one at once, in ſubjection to the Rule of Christ, <hi>1 Cor. 14.26 to 34.</hi> though Prayer is not expreſly mentioned therein) wherefore you do reject the Pſalm expreſly named and annexed with other Gifts unto
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:175970:11"/>the Rule, from coming under the Order of it? And what can you ſay to the Practice of Womens vocal Singing in the Church, when it is ſo directly againſt the plain and poſitive Command of Christ?</p>
            <p>To conclude this Epiſtle to you; it high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly concerns you to conſider whether your pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice of Singing, or what I have herein aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerted in this Treatiſe,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.12, 13, 14, 15. <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.16.</note> can ſtand our Trial at the Day of Jeſus Chriſt, when both you and I ſhall appear before him, and receive our Loſs or Gain according to the Goſpel. And therefore that the Lord would graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly awaken you, and convince you of your Error, (which I am perſwaded that one day or other you will be made aſhamed of) and pardon your Sin and Injury to the Church of Chriſt therein, and prevent your build<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Hay and Stubble on the true Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation, and make you an Inſtrument of his Glory, and his Peoples Comfort, as it hath been my earnest Prayers to God for you, ſo I deſire in Love and Faithfulneſs to continue.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>I. M.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:175970:11"/>
            <head>The CONTENTS of the Brief DISCOURSE, or the Firſt Part.</head>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>1. A</hi> Brief Expoſition of <hi>Epheſ. 5.18, 19. Col. 3.16. 1 Cor. 14.26. Page 5</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>2.</hi> Of the Eſſence or Being of Singing, <hi>Page 5</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>3.</hi> Of <hi>David</hi>'s Pſalms, <hi>Page 9</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>4.</hi> Of Precompoſed Songs and Hymns, <hi>Page 15</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>5.</hi> Of Womens Singing, <hi>Page 21</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>6.</hi> Of the Order of Singing, <hi>Page 22</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>7.</hi> Objections anſwered.
<list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>(1.)</hi> Of <hi>Moſes, Deborah,</hi> and <hi>Barak</hi>'s Sing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>Page 24</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>(2.)</hi> Of Muſick uſed by the Prophets in <hi>Saul</hi>'s Time, <hi>Page 25</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>(3.)</hi> That Muſick and Singing was an Inſtitution to continue till Temple-Worſhip was made void, is no Argument to prove that Goſpel-Singing ſhould continue in conſtant uſe from the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitive Church till the ſecond Coming of Chriſt, <hi>Page 26</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>(4.)</hi> To <hi>Iſa. 52.8, 9. Page 28</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>(5.)</hi> To <hi>Matth. 26.30. Page 29</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>(6.)</hi> To <hi>Acts 16.25. Page 32</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>(7.)</hi> To <hi>Epheſ. 5.19. Page 33</hi>
                     </item>
                     <pb n="22" facs="tcp:175970:12"/>
                     <item>
                        <hi>(8.)</hi> Of Wicked Mens praying and ſinging Praiſes, <hi>Page 36</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>(9.)</hi> That true Believers having cauſe to praiſe God, is no proof that they muſt conſtantly ſing his Praiſe in his Worſhip, <hi>Page 38</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>(10.)</hi> That Formal Prayer and Singing under the Law, is no Argument for ſuch under the Goſpel, <hi>Page 43</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>(11.)</hi> That Prayer, and conſequently Singing, are of the ſame Nature under the Goſpel as they were under the Law, is explained and anſwered, <hi>Page 44</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>(12.)</hi> Precompoſed Forms of Preaching, is no ground for uſing ſuch Forms of Singing, <hi>Page 46</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <head>The CONTENTS of the APPENDIX.</head>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sect. 1.</hi> SHeweth that God was and is otherwiſe praiſed, than by ſinging only, <hi>Page 2</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sect. 2.</hi> That the Word <hi>Hymnos</hi> a Hymn, ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifieth ſimply a Praiſe, <hi>Page 6</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A Diſcourſe of Chriſt's Hymning or Praiſing at his Inſtitution of the Supper, <hi>Page 12</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sect. 3.</hi> Of the Nature of the Command, or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Exhortation to ſing, and that the Singing uſed in the Primitive Church was from a ſpecial Gift of the Holy Spirit: and alſo further proof, that by Old-Teſtament-Names to New-Teſtament-Things, are intended diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent Things than in the Old, <hi>&amp;c. Page 13, 14, 20, 24</hi>
               </item>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:175970:12"/>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sect. 4.</hi> Of praiſing God as a Moral Duty, and from Moral Qualifications only, opened and clearly anſwered, <hi>Page 27</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sect. 5.</hi> Womens Singing is more fully diſcuſſed and confuted, <hi>Page 32</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sect. 6.</hi> A General Anſwer to thoſe Prophetical Places of Scripture, of All the Earths ſinging unto the Lord, <hi>Page 38</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sect. 7.</hi> Premeditated ſtinted Forms for Prayer or Singing, unlawful to be uſed, <hi>Page 38</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sect. 8. Object.</hi> That preſtinted Forms of Sing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing are Spiritual Worſhip, if their matter are agreeable to the Word of God, and if ſung with Grace in our Hearts, opened and an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered, <hi>Page 43</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="notice">
            <head>Advertiſement.</head>
            <p>THere is no Alteration here made in the former Part, or <hi>Brief Diſcourſe</hi> (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore publiſhed) except a larger Expoſition of <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 5.19. See <hi>pag.</hi> 5.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>In Appendix Page 10. Line 26, 27. add to <hi>laudes, dixerunt,</hi> they ſaid Praiſes. Pag. 21. line 3, and 9. to <hi>ſinging,</hi> add <hi>together.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <group>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:175970:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:175970:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <p>A BRIEF DISCOURSE CONCERNING SINGING IN THE Publick Worſhip of GOD IN THE GOSPEL-CHURCH.</p>
                  <p>By <hi>J. M.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for the Author, MDCXC.</p>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="text">
                  <pb facs="tcp:175970:14"/>
                  <pb n="3" facs="tcp:175970:14"/>
                  <head>Concerning <hi>SINGING</hi> in the Worſhip of God.</head>
                  <p>SEeing it hath pleaſed the Almighty God by his ſpecial Providence to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver his poor afflicted People in this Nation out of the Hands of their greateſt Enemies, to ſerve him without fear; what then is expected from us, but that in all things we ſhould ſerve him with one Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, in Holineſs and Righteouſneſs all the Days of our Lives? To which end he hath given us his bleſſed and holy Word as a Rule for our Faith and Practice.</p>
                  <p>But that which is moſt unhappy to many Saints who ſincerely labour for, and long af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the perfect Union of the Church of Chriſt, is, That we cannot all attain to one and the ſame Conception of the Mind and Will of God revealed to us in the holy Scriptures. And though there are divers Things of leſſer moment in which we dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer, yet there are others of greater Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence that ought to be duly weighed in the Ballance of the Sanctuary, leſt through the Imbecillity or Weakneſs of ſome Chriſtians, and by the ſeeming plauſible Arguments of others, there ſhould be a falling away from
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:175970:15"/>the Truth ſo clearly manifeſted to us by the Holy Scriptures, and witneſſed to by the Sufferings of the pureſt Churches in our Age, who have born a lively Teſtimony not only againſt the humane preſcribed and precom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed Forms of Prayers, but of ſinging of <hi>David</hi>'s Pſalms, and other Hymns or Songs precompoſed by Man, as they are frequently uſed as part of the conſtant and ordinary Worſhip of God inſtituted in his Goſpel-Church.</p>
                  <p>This being the Subject of the following Diſcourſe, I ſhall proceed to treat of it with as much Brevity and Clearneſs as I can, to convince the Judgment of the miſtaken Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders (and to confirm and prevent others) from the practice of ſo great an Error as will lead them to Apoſtacy or Backſliding, who in this matter have leſs to ſay for themſelves, than others have who are for a Form of Prayer.</p>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>Epheſ. 5.18, 19.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                     <p>And be not drunk with Wine, wherein is Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs; but be filled with the Spirit: Speaking<note n="*" place="margin">Gr. <hi>In.</hi> See <hi>Pool</hi>'s An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>notations.</note> to your ſelves in Pſalms, and Hymns, and ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Songs, ſinging and making Melody in your Heart to the Lord.</p>
                  </q>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>Col. 3.16.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                     <p>Let the Word of Chriſt dwell in you richly in all Wiſdom; teaching and admoniſhing one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in Pſalms, and Hymns, and ſpiritual Songs, ſinging with Grace in your Hearts to the Lord.</p>
                  </q>
                  <pb n="5" facs="tcp:175970:15"/>
                  <p>That which is needful, before we come to take notice of the ſeveral Heads to be treat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of, is, to conſider of thoſe three Texts which are made a Foundation for a vocal Singing together in the conſtant Worſhip of God in the Goſpel-Church, tho ſome things therein I leave to diſcourſe hereafter.</p>
                  <p n="1">
                     <hi>1ſt.</hi> Epheſ. 5.19. <hi>Speaking to your ſelves in Pſalms, and Hymns, and ſpiritual Songs.</hi> 1. From theſe words there is not any Neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity for a vocal Speaking to be here un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood, but otherwiſe of ſpeaking to your own Heart, as it's ſaid,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.28.</note> 
                     <hi>But if there be no Interpreter, let him keep ſilence in the Church, and let him ſpeak to himſelf, and to God.</hi> So that <hi>ſpeaking to your ſelves,</hi> may be taken, as that is expreſly ſaid to be, of keeping ſilence in the Church, and is not limited to a vocal Speaking. 2. This is farther confirmed, as the aforeſaid Mr. <hi>Pool</hi> in his Annotations read it Gr. <hi>[in,] Speaking [in] your ſelves, in Pſalms, and Hymns, and ſpiritual Songs, ſinging and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king Melody in your Heart to the Lord.</hi> 3. That both the <hi>ſpeaking</hi> and the <hi>Melody</hi> in this Text, cannot be limited to be vocally underſtood, but is inwardly in the Heart, is manifeſt from the preceding part of this Chapter, wherein the holy Apoſtle, naming of divers groſs Sins and Enormities, exhorteth the Church of <hi>Epheſus</hi> to flee from them, and to <hi>have no Fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowſhip with the unfruitful works of Darkneſs, but rather reprove them,</hi> and not to be drunk with Wine, wherein is exceſs, but to be fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led with the Spirit. Whereby it appears,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:175970:16"/>that this Exhortation to the Church of <hi>Ephe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus</hi> to ſpeak to themſelves in Pſalms, and Hymns, and ſpiritual Songs, and to be giving Thanks always,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Ver.</hi> 20.</note> 
                     <hi>&amp;c.</hi> was principally deſign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, that inſtead of Filthineſs and fooliſh Talking and Jeſting, which are mentioned in the former part of the Chapter, they ſhould rather be giving of Thanks,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Ver.</hi> 4.</note> as it is expreſly ſaid; and inſtead of having Fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip with the unfruitful Works of Darkneſs, and being filled with exceſs of Wine, to be filled with the Spirit, and to exerciſe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in private Devotions towards God in Pſalms, and Hymns, and ſpiritual Songs, ſinging and making Melody in their Heart to the Lord. So that from the main deſign of the Apoſtle's Diſcourſe relating to the Text, both the Speaking and the Melo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy here intended is to themſelves, in their Heart: and whether you read the Text ſpeaking <hi>[to]</hi> or ſpeaking <hi>[in]</hi> your ſelves, it cannot neceſſitate a vocal Singing together, but a ſpeaking inwardly in their Hearts. 4. Neither can this Text be taken, as ſome would have it, for a vocal Singing [together,] from the words to <hi>[your ſelves,]</hi> as if that did limit the Text to prove a Singing [together,] any more than <hi>building up your ſelves on your moſt holy Faith,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ude</hi> 20.</note> 
                     <hi>praying in the Holy Ghoſt,</hi> does confine that Text to be underſtood of teaching or edifying one another in a diſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derly way, ſpeaking all together: or that from thoſe words <hi>(your ſelves — praying in the Holy Ghoſt)</hi> ſpoken in general unto the Saints,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:175970:16"/>they are commanded to pray all vocally toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. Moreover, if any ſay that the fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing words, <hi>ver.</hi> 20. <hi>Giving Thanks always for all things unto God and the Father, in the Name of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt;</hi> are explana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory of the former Verſe; and being in ſuch general terms, cannot exclude a vocal Sing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and Thankſgiving to God of the Church all together, from being underſtood there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in: I do make reply, That though ſpeaking to your ſelves in Pſalms, and Hymns, and Spiritual Songs, <hi>ver.</hi> 19. and <hi>Giving Thanks always for all things,</hi> ver. 20. are from the Fillings of the holy Spirit, yet I make a difference between them; for the one is li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mited (to your ſelves, and making Melo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy in your Heart) to private Edifications, Praiſes, and Thankſgivings; but the other is in ſuch general Words as may comprehend all Thankſgiving both vocal, and mental in the Heart. So that the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> is here preſſing the Saints of <hi>Epheſus</hi> to endeavour after a plentiful meaſure of the holy Spirit of Chriſt, and to put forth his Gifts and Graces both in mental, and vocal, in private, and more publick Praiſing and Thankſgiving to God, according to the different occaſions and circumſtances that might attend them.</p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <hi>2dly. Coloſſ.</hi> 3.16. I confeſs that vocal Singing is here to be underſtood, otherwiſe it could not be teaching and admoniſhing to others in Word and Deed, <hi>ver.</hi> 17. but yet herein is nothing to prove a vocal Singing to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether by all the Church: For <hi>teaching and admoniſhing one another in Pſalms, &amp;c.</hi> is meant
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:175970:17"/>of the miniſtring Brethren, whoſe Work and Office it was to teach and admoniſh the other Members, according to the Gift of the Holy Spirit they had received: And none can prove any more by theſe words <hi>[one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,]</hi> than what muſt be underſtood from <hi>Heb.</hi> 3.13. <hi>But exhort one another daily, while it is called, To day, &amp;c.</hi> And therefore as the Word of Exhortation is not uſed in the Service of God in the Church, but in an orderly miniſterial Way, by one at once; ſo <hi>teaching and admoniſhing one another, &amp;c.</hi> muſt be uſed alſo according to Goſpel-Rule, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.30, 31. 3. Nor can 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.26. <hi>How is it then, Brethren, when you come together, eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one of you hath a Pſalm, hath a Doctrine, &amp;c.</hi> be underſtood of a vocal ſinging all together; for I think none will ſay that thoſe words, <hi>Every one of you hath, &amp;c.</hi> were ſpoken of their all having of all thoſe ſpiritual Gifts, which cannot be thought of every Miniſter in that Church, <hi>ver.</hi> 28. and much leſs of all the Members: therefore it follows, that as all the miniſtring Brethren were not ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to have all thoſe Gifts, but every one of them had one or more of the Gifts of the Holy Spirit; ſo there is no Concluſion can be made, that all the Miniſtry had the Gift of Singing, or that there was any diſtinction of its Univerſality in Delivery more than of other Gifts in the ſame Text; beſides, the Context from <hi>ver.</hi> 27, to 32. ſpeaks of ſingle Perſons that muſt exerciſe in the Church, and therefore thoſe words, <hi>Every one of you,</hi> can't be meant of all together.</p>
                  <pb n="5" facs="tcp:175970:17" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <p>That Spiritual and Vocal Singing was u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in the Primitive and Apoſtolical Church of Chriſt, is undeniable; and that ſuch ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual Singing is you allowed, is freely grant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: but the Queſtion is, Whether <hi>David</hi>'s Pſalms, or any humane preſcribed, or pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compoſed Matter, may or ought not to be vocally ſung by all the Church together, as part of the publick, conſtant and ordinary Worſhip of God, inſtituted in his Goſpel-Church. To demonſtrate which, I ſhall treat of theſe ſix Particulars.</p>
                  <list>
                     <item>I. Of the Eſſence or Being of Singing.</item>
                     <item>II. Of <hi>David</hi>'s Pſalms.</item>
                     <item>III. Of preſcribed or precompoſed Songs and Hymns.</item>
                     <item>IV. Of Womens Singing.</item>
                     <item>V. Of the Order of Singing.</item>
                     <item>VI. Of Scriptural and other Objections.</item>
                  </list>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>
                        <hi>I. Of the</hi> Eſſence of Singing.</head>
                     <p>Though intelligible Singing for teaching and admoniſhing others cannot be without the uſe of the Organical Inſtruments of the Voice, yet the <hi>Eſſence</hi> or Being <hi>of Singing</hi> conſiſts in an inward ſpiritual Exerciſe of the Soul or Mind of Man. And this muſt be granted: for we all do own that true Prayer may be made in our Hearts to God without the uſe of our Voice; otherwiſe we deny all worſhipping of God in the Church, ſave only what is done by the Miniſter, and
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:175970:18"/>exclude the Members of it from adding to, joining with, or having any ſhare in Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Worſhip; and conſequently that no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing can be properly called <hi>Sin</hi> that is only in the inward exerciſe of the Spirit, but that which is ſo manifeſted by Words or Deeds. And as I think that none will deny either the Principal, or its contrary Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quences; ſo the Scriptures do clearly wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs that the Eſſence of Prayer and Praiſes, and of Sin, do all conſiſt in an inward Exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe of the Soul or Spirit.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Firſt,</hi> The Eſſence of Sin is in the Spirit; for <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.7.</note> That <hi>he had not known the Sin of Luſt, except the Law had ſaid, Thou ſhalt not covet.</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Pſal.</hi> 94.11</note> And <hi>the Lord knoweth the Thoughts of Man that they are Vanity: And that every Imagination of the Thoughts of his Heart are only evil continually.</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Gen.</hi> 6.5.</note> And Chriſt ſaith, <hi>That whoſoever looketh on a Woman to luſt after her,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.28.</note> 
                        <hi>hath committed Adultery with her already in his Heart.</hi> So that the Eſſence of Sin conſiſts in the corrupt and evil Thoughts and Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginations of the Hearts and Minds of the Sons of Men, tho not expreſſed by Words or Actions.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Secondly,</hi> The <hi>Eſſence of Prayer</hi> is in the Heart or Spirit:<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Neh.</hi> 2.4.</note> for <hi>Nehemiah</hi> while he was in the King's Preſence made his Prayer to God; which moſt rationally muſt be taken for ſecret Ejaculations and Heart-Prayer. And <hi>Hannah</hi> in the bitterneſs of her Soul prayed and <hi>ſpake in her Heart;</hi>
                        <note place="margin">1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 1.13, &amp;c.</note> 
                        <hi>only her Lips moved, but her Voice was not heard.</hi> And <hi>for
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:175970:18"/>the ſighing of the Needy now will I ariſe,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Pſal.</hi> 12.5. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 79.11 <hi>Pſ.</hi> 102.20</note> 
                        <hi>ſaith the Lord. Let the Sighings of the Priſoners come before thee.</hi> And <hi>the Lord heareth their Groanings.</hi> And this kind of Prayer our Lord himſelf uſed; for <hi>looking up to Heaven,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Mar.</hi> 7.34.</note> 
                        <hi>he ſighed</hi> when he was opening the deaf Ears.<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.26</note> And theſe are the Prayers that the Apoſtle calls <hi>unutterable:</hi> for many times there is more in our inward Sighings, Groanings, Longings, Pantings, Breathings, and Suppli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations of Heart and Spirit, than can be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed by our Tongues; and <hi>God looketh on the Heart more than on the outward Appearance:</hi>
                        <note place="margin">1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 16.7</note> for he being a Spirit, ſeeketh ſpiritual Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhippers: <hi>And they that worſhip him,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>John</hi> 4.23, 24.</note> 
                        <hi>muſt wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip him in Spirit and in Truth.</hi> And herein lies the Excellency of a true Chriſtian, who being ſanctified by the Holy Spirit in the Faculties and Powers of his Soul, he out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doth the moſt refined Hypocrite in the World, who may glorify God with his Tongue, while his Soul is deſtitute of the Graces of the Holy Spirit; but the true Chriſtian being <hi>bought with a Price,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.20</note> 
                        <hi>glorifies God not only in his Body, but in his Spirit, which are the Lord's.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Thirdly,</hi> If the Eſſence of Prayer be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly in the Spirit, why not of Singing alſo?<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.15.</note> 
                        <hi>I will pray with the Spirit, and I will pray with the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding alſo: I will ſing with the Spirit, and I will ſing with the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding alſo.</hi> The Apoſtle expreſſes them alike, becauſe their Eſſences are alike in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly in the Soul or Spirit.</p>
                     <pb n="8" facs="tcp:175970:19"/>
                     <p>But ſome will ſay, This is meant of vocal Singing in the Church, and therefore comes ſhort of proving the Eſſence of Singing in the Spirit.</p>
                     <p>True, this is meant of Vocal Prayer and Singing in the Church,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Ver.</hi> 11, 13, 14, 15, 16, 17.</note> which the Apoſtle calls Speaking, <hi>viz.</hi> in Prayer, Singing, and giving Thanks. But in <hi>ver.</hi> 28. it is ſaid, That <hi>if there is no Interpreter, let him keep ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence in the Church, and let him ſpeak to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and to God.</hi> And that this ſpeaking to himſelf, and to God, relates to the Gift of Singing as well as to other Gifts, is mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſted, <hi>ver.</hi> 26, 27. in that, with other Gifts, a Pſalm is there mentioned, and to be deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered or interpreted in a known Tongue: but in caſe there is no Interpreter, then the Pſalm, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> muſt be ſpoken to God, and to himſelf, for improving his own Soul. Now what can be more plain than that Singing and other Gifts of the Holy Spirit, have their Eſſences in our Spirits,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.3.</note> wherein we are capable of worſhipping God without the verbal and vocal Inſtruments of the Body? Moreover, as the Holy Spirit is the Spirit of Prayer; ſo the ſame Spirit is alſo the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of Joy:<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.26.</note> and as there is <hi>unutterable Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er,</hi> ſo there is <hi>unſpeakable Joy,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.8.</note> 
                        <hi>and Rejoicing full of Glory, viz.</hi> inward Glory and Melo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy in the Heart; ſee the Text. The Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of Singing is in the Heart, ſuch as cannot be vocally expreſſed by Words of the Tongue. And though vocal Joy and Sing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing may be teaching to others, yet the
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:175970:19"/>ſpeaking to (Gr. <hi>in</hi>) your ſelves (<hi>viz.</hi> in your own Hearts) <hi>in Pſalms and Hymns, and ſpiritual Songs, ſinging and making Melody in your Hearts to the Lord,</hi> is Muſick of an higher ſtrain, ſurpaſſing all verbal and vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Melody in the Ears of God; as <hi>unſpeaka<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Joy and rejoicing full of Glory,</hi> excels that which is ſpeakable.</p>
                     <p>Indeed we find in Scripture another kind of unſpeakable Singing, which is more in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feriour than this we have treated of, <hi>viz.</hi> the virtual Singing of the Creatures.<note place="margin">1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 16.32, 33.</note> 
                        <hi>Let the Fields rejoice, and all that is therein; Then ſhall the Trees of the Wood ſing out—.</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Pſalm</hi> 65.13.</note> 
                        <hi>The Paſtures are clothed with Flocks; the Vallies al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo are covered over with Corn; they ſhout for Joy, they alſo ſing.</hi> Now if the flouriſhing State of the Creatures, and of the Fruits of the Earth, are called a <hi>Singing,</hi> how much more properly may the harmonious Melody of the Spirit of God with our Spirits be called <hi>Singing,</hi> which is the Eſſence and Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of it.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>
                        <hi>II.</hi> Of <hi>David's</hi> Pſalms.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Firſt,</hi> There was no Inſtitution of Singing before <hi>David</hi>'s time: for though we find the Song of <hi>Moſes,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Deut.</hi> 32. <hi>Ex.</hi> 19.19. <hi>ch.</hi> 20.22. <hi>Gen.</hi> 31.11. <hi>Gen.</hi> 37.7, 8, 9, 10. <hi>ch.</hi> 15.12, 13.</note> containing a prophetical Deſcription of the State and Accidents of the Jewiſh Church for time to come, yet this was no preſent Inſtitution for the Church in the conſtant Service of God, but a way of Conveyance of his Word, which in thoſe
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:175970:20"/>times was in divers manners delivered to us,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Num.</hi> 24.4.</note> 
                        <hi>viz.</hi> by Dreams,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Heb.</hi> 1.1.</note> Viſions, Words, Songs and Muſick, but now by Jeſus Chriſt. And though we find the Songs of <hi>Moſes,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Num.</hi> 12.6, 7.</note> and of <hi>Deborah,</hi> occaſioned from thoſe great Deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verances of the Children of <hi>Iſrael,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">2 <hi>Kings</hi> 3.15.</note> yet none was inſtituted for the Levitical Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip and conſtant Service of God till <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi>'s time,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 10.5.</note> who had prepared, preſcribed and ſet in Order, Matter, Perſons, and Things for the moſt ſplendid and perfect Worſhip of God, and Temple-State of the Church which ſhould be in <hi>Solomon</hi>'s Days. Now as the Law was a Shadow of good things to come, let us ſee what the Jewiſh Church in her Wilderneſs afflicted unſetled Tabernacle-State may be ſaid to prefigure out to us in the caſe of Singing.</p>
                     <p>As for her Minority in the Wilderneſs through Sin and Unbelief, they had many Judgments which did befal them, and cut them ſhort of the promiſed Reſt, ſo that of ſix hundred Thouſand Footmen that came out of <hi>Egypt,</hi> there was but two that en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred into the Land of <hi>Canaan,</hi> wherein there were many Wars and Troubles that did attend them till the latter end of <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi>'s Reign: therefore while the Jewiſh Church met with ſo many Sorrows, Trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles and Afflictions, the Worſhip of God was ſuited to her State; but when they had Reſt from all their Enemies in <hi>David</hi>'s time,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 23.25.</note> and <hi>Solomon</hi> a King of Peace and Type of Chriſt to reign over them, God was pleaſed
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:175970:20"/>to beautify, inlarge, and perfect his Service and Worſhip according to the Temple-State, top-Glory and Happineſs of his Church and People.</p>
                     <p>Now if theſe things were a Figure of Goſpel-times; what may we then ſay, but that as <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Deborah,</hi> for the ſignal Deliverance of that Day, ſung to God through the Gift of the Holy Spirit; ſo the Church of Chriſt under the New Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment have their occaſional Songs, as the 144000, <hi>being the firſt Fruits unto God and to the Lamb,</hi> who ſang not <hi>David</hi>'s Pſalms;<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Rev.</hi> 14.3, 4. <hi>ch.</hi> 5.9.</note> 
                        <hi>for no Man could learn their Song, but the</hi> 144000 <hi>which were redeemed from the Earth.</hi> And the new Song for the opening of the Book of the <hi>Revelations,</hi> and the Song of <hi>Moſes,</hi> and of the Lamb,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>ch.</hi> 15.2, 3, 4, 6, 7.</note> by thoſe that had gotten Victory over the Beaſt, and over his Image, and over his Mark, and over the Number of his Name, about the going forth of the ſeven Vial-Angels with the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven laſt Plagues of the Wrath of God; but none of theſe were <hi>David</hi>'s Pſalms, or do warrant the ſinging of them, or any other precompoſed Songs in Goſpel-times, in the conſtant and ordinary Worſhip of God by all the Church, any more than thoſe particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Songs of <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Deborah</hi> were an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution for the Jewiſh Church for the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Service of God in their Day. For there was no ſuch Inſtitution of Songs in the Wilderneſs, nor while that Church was under Troubles, until <hi>David</hi>'s and <hi>Solomon</hi>'s
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:175970:21"/>time,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Eccl.</hi> 3.11. <hi>Prov.</hi> 25.20.</note> for the Temple-Worſhip. <hi>For every thing is beutiful in his time. As he that taketh away a Garment in cold Weather; ſo is he that ſingeth Songs to an heavy Heart.</hi> And ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times it was unſeaſonable while it was yet an Inſtitution.<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Pſal.</hi> 137.1, 2, 3, &amp;c.</note> 
                        <hi>By the Rivers of</hi> Babylon <hi>there we ſat down,—we hanged our Harps upon the Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows—: They that carried us Captive, required of us to ſing one of the Songs of</hi> Sion. <hi>How ſhall we ſing the Lord's Song in a ſtrange Land? Is any afflicted?</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Jam.</hi> 5.1.</note> 
                        <hi>let him pray: Is any merry? let him ſing Pſalms.</hi> So then if Singing be the expreſſing of Joy, Gladneſs, and Mirth of Spirit, and the Church of Chriſt be now in a Wilderneſs, Mourning, Sackcloth-State; why ſhould we imagine that Chriſt ſhould appoint ſuch an Ordinance for her conſtant univerſal Practice, while ſhe is in ſuch Eſtate that is ſo improper and contrary to her State and Spirit, but that the Typical Glory of the Jewiſh Church in <hi>Solomon</hi>'s time ſhall be compleatly anſwered in the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal and ſpiritual Glory of the Church of Chriſt in her Kingdom-State.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Secondly,</hi> The Singing of <hi>David</hi>'s Pſalms were ſuitable to all the reſt of the Levitical, Ceremonial, and external inſtituted Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of God in the Old-Teſtament-Church, in its moſt perfect ſplendant State in <hi>David</hi>'s and <hi>Solomon</hi>'s Days, conſiſting of a wordly Temple;<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.9, 10, 23. &amp; <hi>ch.</hi> 7.12. <hi>ch.</hi> 8.13. <hi>ch.</hi> 10.1.</note> for if the Sanctuary was worldly, the Temple was alſo worldly; and of car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Ordinances, which was a Figure for the time then preſent, and Pattern of Heavenly
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:175970:21"/>things, and Shadow of good things to come, but not the very Image of the things; and were impoſed on them until the time of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation, and change of the Prieſthood, Law, Temple, and Service, or Worſhip of God; which things being all removed by Chriſt the Body and Subſtance of them,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Acts</hi> 15.10.28. <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.6.</note> who hath taken off that Yoak, and delivered us from the Law, that we ſhould ſerve in New<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Spirit, and not in the Oldneſs of the Letter,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.6.</note> to bring in any part of the Levitical Ceremonial Inſtitutions into Goſpel-Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip; for that is a mingling of Letter and Spirit, of Law and Goſpel together.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Thirdly, David</hi>'s Pſalms were inſtituted, appointed and appropriated, not only to vocal Singing, but to divers kinds of muſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Inſtruments, which are all named,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 15.16 <hi>to</hi> 25. <hi>See Dutch Annot. on Pſal.</hi> 9. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 22. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 16. &amp; 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 15.20, 21. 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 13. <hi>ch.</hi> 14. <hi>ch.</hi> 28.12, 13.</note> 
                        <hi>viz.</hi> Cymbals, Harps, Pſalteries and Trumpets, together with vocal Singing; and limited by the Spirit, as divers are of opinion, to certain Tunes or Parts of Muſick, ordained and commanded by the Spirit of God, and of as great Force as Singing was. And therefore to follow the Old-Teſtament-In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution of <hi>David</hi>'s Pſalms, there will be a Neceſſity of having <hi>David</hi>'s Inſtruments of Muſick, and Tunes or Parts; and of the Courſes and ſeveral Orders of the <hi>Levites:</hi> which Antichriſt ſomewhat imitates, mix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing together the Chriſtian, Jewiſh, and Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan Religion, inſtead of conforming to the true Apoſtolical Inſtitutions and Pattern of Divine Worſhip.</p>
                     <pb n="14" facs="tcp:175970:22"/>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Fourthly,</hi> The matter of <hi>David</hi>'s Pſalms, and of other Holy Mens, contained in the ſame Book, ſuited to the Levitical Service, and not to Goſpel-Worſhip; for many of them were ſuited to particular Occaſions and Experiences, and Accidents of that Day, as you may ſee by divers of their Titles; others were general, of <hi>Iſrael</hi>'s Deliverance out of <hi>Egypt,</hi> and from divers other Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies. Some were clear Prophecies of the Sufferings of Chriſt (which to ſing now were to deny that Chriſt is come in the Fleſh) and of his Church, and the Glory that ſhould follow, under the Types and Names of <hi>David</hi> and <hi>Solomon;</hi> and many legal things, in which Goſpel-Myſteries are wrapped up: ſome of which are hard to be underſtood by the greateſt Proficients of our Day; and therefore improper to be ſung by all the Church, who can't ſing them with Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding; and others of them being Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers and miſerable Complainings, may as well juſtify the ſinging Prayers as finging Praiſes.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Fifthly,</hi> The Pſalms of <hi>David</hi> were li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mited to Perſons, <hi>viz.</hi> the <hi>Levites,</hi> who were the Miniſters of the Songs,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 29.25, <hi>&amp;c. to</hi> 31. 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 16.4. <hi>to</hi> 8. <hi>&amp; ver.</hi> 36. <hi>ch.</hi> 25. 1 <hi>to</hi> 8. <hi>ver.</hi> 36, 41. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 106.48.</note> both by Voice and Muſical Inſtruments; for the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple did not ſing together with the <hi>Levites,</hi> but only bowed the Head and worſhipped, and concluded with <hi>Amen,</hi> and praiſed the Lord with <hi>Amen, Hallelujah;</hi> or, <hi>Amen, Praiſe ye the Lord.</hi> Therefore from this Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidical Inſtitution there is no Ground, Pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tern, or Example, for the Goſpel-Churich to ſing together.</p>
                     <pb n="15" facs="tcp:175970:22"/>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Sixthly,</hi> Such ſinging the Pſalms of <hi>David</hi> is no where inſtituted, ordained or practiſed, either by Chriſt or his Holy Apoſtles; there is no Inſtance can be given in the New Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment that any of <hi>David</hi>'s Pſalms were ever ſung by any Perſons or Churches, or that Chriſt or his Holy Apoſtles did ever uſe them, but as they did other Scriptures; or that the Holy Apoſtles when ever they had occaſion to tranſlate any one Text out of the <hi>Hebrew</hi> into the <hi>Greek</hi> Tongue, did ever turn them into Metre; and therefore find<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing no Inſtitution nor Example, we have no Warrant for the Singing of them.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>
                        <hi>III.</hi> Of preſcribed and precompoſed Songs and Hymns.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Firſt,</hi> If the Eſſence of Singing (as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore is ſhewed) conſiſteth in an inward ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual Exerciſe of the Soul or Mind of Man, and that (as I ſhall farther demonſtrate) both the Matter and the Melody of it pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedeth from the inward Graces and Opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the Holy Spirit with the Word; then ſurely no humane preſcribed or pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compoſed form of Singing can be accepted of God, but that which proceedeth from the Word of God, by the Dictates and Teachings of the Holy Spirit, which is ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt from thoſe two Texts, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 5.18, 19. <hi>Col.</hi> 3.16. ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>Be filled with the Spirit—. Let the Word of Chriſt dwell richly in you, in all Wiſdom,</hi> &amp;c. Here is
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:175970:23"/>the Fountain of Goſpel-Worſhip, <hi>viz.</hi> the Word and Spirit of Chriſt, not the Word alone, for that cannot inrich the Soul in all Wiſdom, without the Spirit of Wiſdom to underſtand it: for to have the Word in the Head only, is but a poor thing, but we muſt have it to dwell richly in our Hearts by the Holy Spirit, to ſing with the Underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and with Grace in our Hearts to the Lord. And as the Word in the Head only cannot create Melody in the Heart without a Fullneſs of the Spirit; ſo the Spirit works not without the Word, but fills us with mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter from the Word, and is witneſſed to by the Word; otherwiſe we know not the Spirit of Truth from the Spirit of Error. Now the Eſſence of Singing conſiſteth of theſe two Parts, <hi>viz.</hi> Matter from the Word, and Melody by the Spirit; ſo that neither the Word nor the Holy Spirit can be wanting: and therefore whatſoever Forms are uſed which proceed not from within us, out of a Fulneſs and Enrichings of the Word and Spirit, cannot be ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Goſpel-Singing.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Secondly,</hi> That no humane preſcribed or precompoſed Forms are to be uſed in Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel-Prayer or Singing, appears from the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtration and Conveyance of the Spirit and Power by the Goſpel.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Firſt,</hi> The Goſpel conveys the Spirit, as <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>Who alſo hath made us able Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters of the New Teſtament, not of the Letter, but of the Spirit; for the Letter killeth, but the
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:175970:23"/>Spirit giveth Life,</hi> or quickneth. Here the Law is called the Letter, and the Goſpel, Spirit; not becauſe the Law was not ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual, and the Goſpel was not tranſcribed in the Letter; but <hi>1ſt,</hi> Becauſe the Law re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired <hi>perfect Obedience</hi> to the Letter, on Pain of Eternal Death, and the Goſpel <hi>ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere Obedience</hi> through the Spirit. <hi>2dly,</hi> Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Legal Worſhip was more formal in the Letter, than the Goſpel-Miniſtration, which is in Spirit. <hi>For we are the Circumci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, which worſhip God in the Spirit—; and have no Confidence in the Fleſh, viz.</hi> in the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mal and carnal Ordinances of the Law, and much leſs in the humane precompoſed forms of Men. <hi>3dly,</hi> Becauſe the Law did not miniſter nor convey the Spirit to us it commanded in the Letter, but gave no ſpiritual Power to perform Obedience to it, which the Goſpel did, by giving the Spirit with the Word. Therefore the Apoſtle calls the Goſpel, <hi>the Law of the Spirit of Life.</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.2.</note> And it is not through the Works of the Law that we receive the Spirit, nor mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter the Spirit, but through the hearing of Faith.<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.2, 5, 14.</note> And this agrees with that great Commiſſion which Chriſt himſelf gave to his Diſciples, <hi>Go ye therefore and teach all Nations —. Lo,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Math.</hi> 28.19, 20.</note> 
                        <hi>I am with you always even to the End of the World.</hi> Not only by his outward Providence, which is over others as well as they, but by his Spirit, which ſhall abide with us for ever.<note place="margin">
                           <hi>John.</hi> 14.16.</note> And the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet ſaith, <hi>As for me this is my Covenant with
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:175970:24"/>them ſaith the Lord, My Spirit that is upon thee, and my Words which I have put in thy Mouth, ſhall not depart out of thy Mouth, nor out of the Mouth of thy Seed, nor out of the Mouth of thy Seeds Seed, ſaith the Lord, from henceforth and for ever.</hi> Here the Word and the Holy Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit are conveyed throughout all Generations to the end of the World, by the Covenant or Goſpel of Jeſus Chriſt. And as none can ſay that the Words which the Lord had put in his Mouth, were a humane preſcribed form: but, as Chriſt himſelf ſaith,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>John</hi> 6.63.</note> 
                        <hi>The Words that I ſpeak unto you, they are Spirit, and they are Life:</hi> So the ſame Words pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding from us by the ſame Spirit, are Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, in oppoſition to humane and legal forms, which reject and deny the ſufficient ſucceſſive Gifts of the Spirit. So that it is clearly mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt, that the ſufficient Gifts of the Holy Spirit do ſtill remain, and ſhall remain, for the Service and Worſhip of God, to the end of the World.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Secondly;</hi> The Goſpel doth miniſter and convey Power. For where the Spirit is, there will be Power. The Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>Ye have not received the Spirit of Bondage</hi> (viz. of the Law) <hi>again to fear;</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.15, 16.</note> 
                        <hi>but ye have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived the Spirit of Adoption, whereby we cry, Abba, Father.</hi> The Spirit gave a ſufficient Power not only to the Apoſtles as ſuch, or to the Saints in <hi>Rome,</hi> as partaking of the extraordinary Gifts of the Holy Spirit in that preſent Day, but, <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.6. <hi>Becauſe ye are Sons, God hath ſent forth the Spirit of
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:175970:24"/>his Son into your Hearts, crying, Abba, Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</hi> Here is the Reaſon of their Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, <hi>becauſe ye are Sons:</hi> therefore all that are Sons according to the meaſure of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of Adoption, which beareth Witneſs with our Spirits that we are the Children of God, have Power to pray to God as to their Father.<note place="margin">2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.7.</note> 
                        <hi>For God hath not given us the Spirit of Fear, but of Power, and of Love, and of a ſound Mind.</hi>
                        <note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.19, 20.</note> 
                        <hi>And the Kingdom of God is not in Word, but in Power.</hi> There were ſome in the Church of <hi>Corinth</hi> that were puffed up in their Minds, whoſe Speech the Apoſtle would not know or regard: but the Power of Religion was that which he looked for, and did expect to find amongſt them; becauſe the Kingdom of God (<hi>viz.</hi> his Goſpel-Church) is not in Word, but in Power. A humane preſcribed Form is no Power, and therefore is none of this Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel-Kingdom. <hi>Jude</hi> 19. <hi>Theſe are they that ſeparate themſelves ſenſual, having not the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit.</hi> And the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> propheſied of ſuch a profeſſing People that ſhould ariſe in the laſt Days; <hi>Having a form of Godlineſs,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.5.</note> 
                        <hi>but denying the Power thereof;</hi> and <hi>from ſuch</hi> we muſt <hi>turn away.</hi> They had an outward Form of Godlineſs, but not the inward Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er; contrary to true Godlineſs, which hath its Form from the inward Power and Work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of the Holy Spirit with the Word. Now it is no Wonder that this formal People deny the Power of Godlineſs; for an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented Form, and the Power are Oppoſites,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:175970:25"/>and are inconſiſtent with each other: for if there be a ſpiritual Power, it refuſes and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies the invented Form; for then there is no need of a preſcribed nor pre-compoſed hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Form: and if we uſe ſuch a Form, we deny the Power, and reject the ſufficient ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſive Gifts of the Holy Spirit, by relying on that Form. And ſo the Apoſtle argues, that <hi>as</hi> Jannes <hi>and</hi> Jambres <hi>withſtood</hi> Moſes, <hi>ſo do theſe reſiſt the Truth:</hi>
                        <note place="margin">2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.8.</note> 
                        <hi>Men of corrupt Minds, Reprobate concerning the Faith.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Thirdly,</hi> Seeing that thoſe Perſons with whom I am chiefly concerned, do not only op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, deny, and refuſe the Uſe of a humane preſcribed and precompoſed Form of Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, but alſo of that Prayer which our Lord taught his Diſciples; of which they rightly ſay, that it was but an Epitome of all Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, and was never intended to confine Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er to the Compaſs and Form of thoſe Words. For we find that none of thoſe many Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers in the New Teſtament were ſo limited, but according to the State and Circumſtances of Perſons and things, they made Supplica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion by the Holy Spirit: and ſo muſt Singing alſo be left to the Liberty of the Holy Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of God. And one might think that I need not uſe farther Arguments; for their own Practice confutes their Error in Singing preſcribed Forms, and teſtifies the Truth I am pleading for: for what Reaſon can be given for Forms of Singing, when they deny all Forms of Prayer? and how can they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject a Form of Prayer, or the Form of
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:175970:25"/>Prayer which Chriſt hath left us in the New Teſtament, while they maintain the uſe of a humane Form of Singing, which is no where found in the Holy Scriptures?</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>
                        <hi>IV. Of</hi> Womens Singing.</head>
                     <p>That Women ought neither to teach nor pray vocally in the Church of Chriſt, is ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally believed by all Orthodox Chriſtians, and is aſſerted from 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.34, 35. <hi>Let your Women keep ſilence in the Churches: for it is not permitted unto them to ſpeak:</hi> And 1 Tim. 2.11, 12. <hi>Let the Women learn in Silence with all Subjection: but I ſuffer not a Woman to teach, nor to uſurp Authority over the Man, but to learn in ſilence.</hi> I therefore greatly mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vel that any Man ſhould aſſert and admit of ſuch a Practice as Womens Singing; and that any Woman ſhould preſume to ſing vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally in the Church of Chriſt, when he poſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tively and plainly forbids them in his Word: for Singing is Teaching, <hi>Coloſſ.</hi> 3.16. and Speaking, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 5.19. both of which are plainly forbidden to Women in the Church. And beſides, they are commanded <hi>to learn in ſilence with all Subjection.</hi> And if this be not Truth, I am at a loſs how to find it. And ſuch as deny the Authority of theſe Scriptures to forbid Womens Singing, do of neceſſity deſtroy the Authority of the Word of God, and leave us deſtitute of a Rule of Worſhip.</p>
                     <pb n="22" facs="tcp:175970:26"/>
                     <p>But ſome may ſay, <hi>Were there not Singing-Women in the Time of the Law?</hi> True, we read of Singing-Women; but as there was no Inſtitution of them amongſt the Prieſts and Levites, who were ſet apart by Name in their ſeveral Orders; ſo we find them no where concerned as ſuch in the Worſhip of God, but either for Mirth and Delight, or as Mourners for the Dead, in which they were very skilful in making of Lamentations both by Voice and Inſtruments of Muſick, as was the Jewiſh Cuſtom: which you may plainly ſee by theſe Scriptures, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 19.35. 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 35.25. <hi>Jer.</hi> 9.17, 18. <hi>Amos</hi> 5.16. <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 2.1, 8. <hi>Mat.</hi> 9.23.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>
                        <hi>V. Of the</hi> Order of Singing.</head>
                     <p>This we have plainly and clearly delivered to us in 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.26 to 34. <hi>How is it then, Brethren? when ye come together, every one of you hath a Pſalm, hath a Doctrine, hath a Tongue, hath a Revelation, hath an Interpretation. Let all things be done to Edifying.</hi> Here the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle ſpeaks of the ſeveral Gifts of the Holy Spirit, and lays down a general Order for their Delivery. 1. The Tongue muſt be by two, or at moſt by three, and that by courſe: <hi>And let one interpret;</hi> that is, That in caſe there were many could ſpeak with Tongues, they ſhould not all exerciſe, to take up the whole time with that Gift, but only two or three of them, and that by courſe or turns. <hi>And if any thing be revealed to another, that
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:175970:26"/>ſitteth by, let the first hold his Peace: for ye may all propheſie one by one:</hi> the <hi>Dutch</hi> tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlate it, <hi>one after another.</hi> Here is the Rule for our Practice, <hi>one by one,</hi> or, <hi>one af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter another,</hi> by courſe or turns, they may ſpeak with Tongues, and propheſy. And though only theſe two Gifts are particula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rized in the Rule, yet the Order ſtands for all the reſt, as having relation to it. The univerſal Practice of all Chriſtians allows this Order in the Gift of Doctrine, and we our ſelves in the Gift of Prayer, that but one is to pray at once. And therefore ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that this Order is obſerved in the Gift of Prayer, which is not mentioned amongſt thoſe ſeveral Gifts; then ſurely we muſt al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low the Pſalm, as one of thoſe Gifts named in the Text, and relating to the Rule to be delivered after the ſame Order appointed for the other Gifts. And there is not the leaſt colour of pretence why any ſhould break the Rule in one of theſe Gifts more than others, but that as they are named to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, and a general Order appointed for their Uſe and Delivery in the Church, ſo it muſt be obſerved for the Pſalm, as well as for any other of thoſe ſpiritual Gifts. And if I ſhould ſee a Song delivered by the Gift of the Holy Spirit in this Order, I hope I ſhould bloſs the Lord for ſo great a Preſence of his Spirit amongſt his People.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <pb n="24" facs="tcp:175970:27"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>VI.</hi> Objections Anſwered.</head>
                     <p>Firſt Objection is, <hi>That</hi> Moſes, <hi>and</hi> Debo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rah <hi>and</hi> Barah, <hi>ſang together with the Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of</hi> Iſrael: <hi>and therefore it was in uſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore</hi> David<hi>'s Time in the Church.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Anſwer</hi> 1. It is certain that <hi>Moſes</hi> delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red his Song by the Gift of the Holy Spirit, and wrote it,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Exod.</hi> 15.1</note> as he did other Scriptures, for a Memorial of <hi>Iſrael</hi>'s Deliverance to future Ages: but that it was then brought in, or any part thereof, till <hi>David</hi>'s Time, to the Levitical Service in the ordinary Worſhip of God, is no where evident. Nor can this Singing be any Rule either for Levitical or Goſpel-Inſtitution: for then we muſt bring in Dancing as well as Singing; for <hi>Miriam</hi> the Propheteſs, the Siſter of <hi>Aaron,</hi> took a Timbrel in her Hand, and all the Women went out after her with Timbrels, and with Dances.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. If we ſhould ſuppoſe that <hi>Moſes, Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riam</hi> and <hi>Iſrael</hi> ſang vocally together at one and the ſame time; we may rather take it for an extraordinary Exſtaſy of Mirth, Joy, and Gladneſs before the Lord, expreſſed by Dancing as well as Singing, (as <hi>David</hi> when he danced before the Ark,) than for any part of inſtituted Worſhip.</p>
                     <p n="3">3. If we ſhould conclude that all <hi>Iſrael</hi> did not vocally ſing with <hi>Moſes,</hi> but thoſe whoſe Hearts the Lord had touched with a ſenſe of that great Deliverance joined in
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:175970:27"/>Spirit with him,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Acts</hi> 2.42.</note> it is no more than what is evident from the like manner of Speech of the three thouſand new Converts that conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued ſtedfaſtly in the Apoſtles Doctrine and Fellowſhip, and in breaking of Bread, and in Prayer: for they did not all vocally pray together, nor actually break Bread; but join<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with, and partook of thoſe Ordinances by the Miniſtry. So that if you take it in either ſenſe, it will make nothing for the eſtabliſhing of a vocal Singing together in Goſpel-Worſhip.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Secondly,</hi> It is ſaid,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Judg.</hi> 5.1.</note> It is ſaid, <hi>Then ſang</hi> Deborah <hi>and</hi> Barak: But <hi>Deborah</hi> did only vocally ſing, and <hi>Barak</hi> joined in Spirit with her in the chiefeſt part of the Song: for how could <hi>Barak</hi> call himſelf <hi>Deborah?</hi> ſaying, <hi>
                           <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ntil that I</hi> Deborah <hi>aroſe, that I aroſe a Mother in</hi> Iſrael? And it is plain that ſhe only did vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally ſing unto the Lord, <hi>ver.</hi> 12. <hi>Awake, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wake,</hi> Deborah; <hi>awake, awake, utter a Song: Ariſe</hi> Barak, <hi>and lead thy Captivity captive, thou Son of</hi> Abinoam.</p>
                     <p>Second Objection is, <hi>That in</hi> Saul<hi>'s Time Muſick was uſed by the Prophets;</hi>
                        <note place="margin">1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 10.5</note> 
                        <hi>and therefore why not Singing and Muſick too in their Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Anſwer.</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Numb.</hi> 11.16, 24, 26, <hi>Ex.</hi> 24.11.</note> As others beſides the Levites were Prophets; ſo I do not find that any of thoſe Prophets were Levites, to whom alone both the Songs and Muſick were afterwards limi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, as the Miniſters thereof in God's Service: and there being neither Inſtitution nor Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice of it to be found, we have no ground
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:175970:28"/>to believe that it was in uſe in the conſtant Worſhip of God before <hi>David</hi>'s Time.</p>
                     <p>Third Objection is, That if Muſick and Singing commences its Date from <hi>David</hi>'s Inſtitution, and was to continue for conſtant Temple-Worſhip, till Temple and Temple-Service was made void, by the Coming of Jeſus Chriſt to erect a more ſpiritual Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip; why ſhould not Goſpel-Singing conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue in conſtant uſe while Goſpel-Temple re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains, <hi>viz. till the ſecond Coming of Jeſus Chriſt without Sin unto Salvation?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Anſwer</hi> 1. As God did ſeparate literal <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael</hi> from the <hi>Egyptians,</hi> and all other Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Exod.</hi> 19.5, 6.</note> to be his peculiar Treaſure and King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of Prieſts, to worſhip him: ſo by the firſt Promulgation of the Goſpel, he called his Church out of the World, and ſeparated them <hi>as a Choſen Generation,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.5, 9.</note> for <hi>a Royal Holy Prieſthood</hi> and Nation, to worſhip him ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his Will.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. Though the words <hi>Temple</hi> and <hi>Taber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacle</hi> are variouſly uſed in the New Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and ſometimes for one and the ſame Thing and State of the Goſpel-Church;<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Heb.</hi> 8.</note> yet the Apoſtle doth plainly ſhow that the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dication of the Tabernacle by <hi>Moſes</hi> with the Blood of the Firſt Teſtament, was the Patern and Figure of the Erection and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dication of the Goſpel-Church,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Chap.</hi> 9.</note> the Heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Tabernacle, by the Blood of the Second Teſtament, <hi>viz.</hi> of Jeſus Chriſt; ſo that the firſt ſetting up of the Goſpel-Church is not the Antitype of <hi>David</hi>'s and <hi>Solomon</hi>'s
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:175970:28"/>Temple, but of <hi>Moſes</hi>'s Tabernacle; and <hi>Solomon</hi>'s Temple is a Figure of greater things to come.</p>
                     <p n="3">3. As in the time of the Levitical Taber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacle-Worſhip, Singing was not eſtabliſhed as part of that conſtant Service, but was on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly a Gift on extraordinary Occaſions, till the more glorious and perfect Temple-State of the Church ſhould be erected: ſo under the firſt Inſtitution of Goſpel-Worſhip there were extraordinary Gifts of Singing, ſuita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to the then extraordinary Circumſtances and Preſence of God in his Church, which may poſſibly on extraordinary Occaſions, now and then on freſh Effuſions of the Holy Spirit, ſtill appear in the Church in her now not perfect Temple, but rather Tabernacle-State, till this be ended, and that more glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious and perfect ſpiritual Temple and Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple-Worſhip, whatever it be, ſhall be erect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, when the Winter of Afflictions is paſt,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Cant.</hi> 2.11, 12.</note> and the time of ſinging of Birds is come, at the Appearing and Kingdom of Jeſus Chriſt, in which time there ſhall be the moſt glorious Perfection and full Completion of the ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Temple and Worſhip of God that ever was or ſhall be extant upon Earth.</p>
                     <p n="4">4. And as the Old Teſtament-Tabernacle-State of the Church was to be beautified, perfected and enlarged in the Temple-State and Temple-Worſhip, and was to continue till the Change and Tranſlation of it into the Goſpel-Church or Kingdom of Heaven: ſo this Goſpel-Tabernacle-Church-State ſhall
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:175970:29"/>be perfected, inlarged, and beautified in the glorious New-<hi>Jeruſalem</hi>-Temple and Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of God, which ſhall continue to the end of the World, and then be tranſlated into the Eternal Kingdom of Heaven. Now as <hi>David</hi> and <hi>Solomon</hi> were Types of Chriſt; and the Old-Teſtament-Temple and Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip were Shadows of the New-<hi>Jeruſalem</hi>-Temple and Worſhip of God in the thouſand Years: So the Inſtitution of Singing in the Levitical Temple-Worſhip, ſhall be compleat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly anſwered in the glorious Antitype and ſpiritual Temple-State in the thouſand Years of Chriſt's Kingdom here on Earth, after ſuch manner as God ſhall be pleaſed to appoint for ſuitable Worſhip to that Day, when the whole Creation that now groaneth under the Bondage of Corruption, ſhall be then delivered into the glorious Liberty of the Sons of God.<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.21, 22.</note>
                     </p>
                     <p>Fourth Objection is from <hi>Iſa.</hi> 52.8, 9. <hi>Thy Watchmen ſhall lift up the Voice, with the Voice together ſhall they ſing: for they ſhall ſee Eye to Eye, when the Lord ſhall bring again</hi> Zion. <hi>Break forth into Joy, ſing together ye waſte Places of</hi> Jeruſalem: <hi>for the Lord hath comforted his People, he hath redeemed</hi> Jeruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem. From whence ſome do aſſert a Sing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing together in the Goſpel-Church.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. That this Scripture hath no pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per Relation to the meer Goſpel-<hi>Sion</hi> and Gentile-<hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> is clear from the Text it ſelf, which ſpeaks of the waſte Places of <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem,</hi> and Redemption of literal <hi>Jeruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem,</hi>
                        <pb n="29" facs="tcp:175970:29"/>the Captive Daughter of <hi>Zion,</hi> when there ſhall no more come into her the Uncir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſed, and the Unclean; which cannot be accompliſhed until the Return of literal <hi>Iſrael</hi> into their Kingdom-State at the ſecond Coming of Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. Then <hi>her Watchmen;</hi> it is not ſaid her People, but her Watchmen, <hi>viz.</hi> her Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets and Miniſters, they ſhall ſing together. The <hi>Dutch</hi> Tranflation reads it, they ſhall <hi>jubile,</hi> or cry, or ſhout for Joy, or rejoice together: and <hi>verſe</hi> 9. they tranſlate, make ye a noiſe or ſound, <hi>jubile,</hi> or ſhout for Joy together, ye waſte Places of <hi>Jeruſalem.</hi> Which Scripture moſt properly relates to the great <hi>Jubile,</hi> or thouſand Years of Chriſt's Kingdom; and cannot be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood of a conſtant vocal Singing together by all the Church in the Worſhip of God in the Goſpel-Tabernacle-State.</p>
                     <p>Fifth Objection is from thoſe Words, <hi>Matth.</hi> 26.30. <hi>And when they had ſung an Hymn,</hi> &amp;c. From whence they do aſſert, that Chriſt and his Diſciples ſung an Hymn vocally together.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. The Word <hi>ſung</hi> is not in the Greek, but it is there read, <hi>And they having hymned;</hi> which Word is taken by divers learned Men to be of a general Signification of all kinds of Praiſes or Thankſgivings, and not confined to Songs only. Some of our old Engliſh Tranſlators read that Text, <hi>And when they had ſaid Grace.</hi> And the <hi>Dutch,</hi> do not limit the word <hi>Hymnos</hi> only to
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:175970:30"/>Songs of Praiſe, but do admit of it to ſignify ſaying Thanks,<note place="margin">See Dutch Annot. on Eph. <hi>5.19.</hi>
                        </note> or Thank-giving to God.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. There is no Reaſon to conclude that the Diſciples vocally ſung together with Chriſt; but that Chriſt as their Miniſter hymned, and they in their Spirits joined with him:<note place="margin">1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 1.11, 13.</note> 
                        <hi>as</hi> Hannah <hi>ſaid:—And ſpake in her Heart:</hi> for I have not met with any of our Reformed, how zealous ſoever they are to promote a vocal Singing together, that will admit that the Diſciples, in <hi>Acts</hi> 4.24, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> prayed all vocally together; but that they lift up their Voice by their Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter, with whom they joyned only in Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, but not with Voice: Notwithſtanding the Text is ſtronger for it, than any Text in the New Teſtament is for their way of Singing: read the Text, <hi>ver.</hi> 23, 24. <hi>And being let go, they went to their own Company, and reported all that the Chief Prieſts and El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders had ſaid unto them. And when they heard that, they lift up their Voice to God with one Accord,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Ver. <hi>31.</hi>
                        </note> 
                        <hi>and ſaid,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>And when they had prayed, the Place was ſhaken,</hi> &amp;c. It is here ſaid, <hi>they lift up their Voice to God with one Accord:</hi> But in <hi>Matth.</hi> 26. it is only ſaid, <hi>They hymned.</hi> Now if the word <hi>[they]</hi> muſt prove their vocal Singing together with Chriſt, much more will thoſe words, <hi>[They lift up their Voice to God with one Accord and ſaid]</hi> prove their vocal Praying together. And let me plainly tell you, that if you aſſert a vocal Singing together from <hi>Matth.</hi> 26. you cannot deny a vocal Praying together from
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:175970:30"/>
                        <hi>Acts</hi> 4. And if you aſſert a preſcribed Form of Singing, you cannot poſſibly avoid the bringing in of a Form of Prayer: for the ſame Arguments uſed for the one, will ſerve to promote the other, with this Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage, that we have a form of Prayer pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed by Chriſt himſelf in the New Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, but none of Singing, except what relates to thoſe myſterious Prophecies in the Book of the <hi>Revelations,</hi> which are no Rule for conſtant Singing.</p>
                     <p>But leſt any weak Chriſtians ſhould from hence imagine that there is ſome ground for a vocal Praying together, as the manner of ſome is, I ſhall ſay ſomething farther, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrate that this Prayer was not made by all the Church vocally together, but by the Miniſter only, as their Voice to God. For the proper Signification of the words can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be otherwiſe underſtood; It is ſaid <hi>[they]</hi> in the plural Number, becauſe not only the Miniſter, but the whole Church did with one Accord and Agreement of Spirit lift up <hi>their Voice</hi> (Gr. <hi>the Voice</hi>) to God; not Voices, in the plural Number, for then all did vocally pray together, but Voice, in the ſingular Number; ſo that though many were of one Accord in Spirit, yet they all had but one ſingle Voice, <hi>viz.</hi> of their Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter, which they, by Agreement of Spirit with him, lifted up, as their Mouth to God in Prayer. And after this manner the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle proveth that the Promiſes made to <hi>Abraham</hi>'s Seed,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.16, 29.</note> were made to Chriſt, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:175970:31"/>they were made to <hi>Abraham,</hi> and to his Seed, in the ſingular Number. And therefore if the Apoſtle proveth that the Promiſes were made to Chriſt from the Word <hi>Seed,</hi> as of one, in the ſingular Number, there is as much Reaſon to aſſert that the Word <hi>Voice</hi> was put in the ſingular Number; properly to explain that by one voice they expreſſed themſelves to God in u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanimous Prayer. And we find that the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of God uſeth the ſingular and plural Num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, not ſo much to follow the Grammatical Rules of humane Learning, as to expreſs and demonſtrate the Truth to us, as <hi>Gen.</hi> 1.1.<note place="margin">See <hi>Willi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am Street,</hi> in his di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viding of the Hoof.</note> 
                        <hi>Elohim Bara,</hi> the Almighties he created; which is ſignificantly expreſſed for our learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, that a Plurality of Divine Perſons, the Trinity in the Unity of Eſſence, were con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned and wrought together in the Works of Creation. So that theſe ſeeming Diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties do not ariſe from any real Abſurdities or Errors in the Holy Sriptures, but from our Iguorance and want of Light to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand the Myſteries of God contained in them.</p>
                     <p>Sixth Objection is from <hi>Acts</hi> 16.25. <hi>And at Midnight</hi> Paul <hi>and</hi> Silas <hi>prayed, and ſang Praiſes unto God; and the Priſoners heard them.</hi> Here alſo the word <hi>[ſang]</hi> is not found in the Greek Tongue, and the Word <hi>hymnos,</hi> is to praiſe; they prayed and praiſed God in Prayer ſo loud, that the Priſoners heard them. And as this could not be by a preſcribed form, for then we ſhould deny
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:175970:31"/>them to have a ſufficient Gift of the Holy Spirit; ſo there is no Evidence that they prayed and praiſed vocally both together, but while the one prayed and praiſed, the other might only joyn in Spirit, and ſo each of them might vocally pray and praiſe the Lord by turns.</p>
                     <p>Seventh Objection is from <hi>Eph.</hi> 5.19.<note place="margin">See <hi>Ainſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worths</hi> An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not. on Pſa. <hi>3.</hi>
                        </note> 
                        <hi>Speaking to</hi> (Gr. <hi>in</hi>) <hi>your ſelves in Pſalms, and Hymns, and ſpiritual Songs,</hi> &amp;c. which three Words are three ſeveral ſorts of Titles of Pſalms, taken out of the Book of Pſalms, <hi>viz. 1ſt.</hi> in Heb. <hi>Mizmore,</hi> Gr. <hi>Pſalmos,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Hymns or Praiſe. Pſa. <hi>145.</hi> Songs, Pſa. <hi>30.</hi> Pſalm <hi>45.</hi> Pſal. <hi>48.120, &amp;c.</hi> to Pſ. <hi>134.</hi> Pſalms, on many other Pſalms.</note> Engl. <hi>Pſalm. 2dly.</hi> in Heb. <hi>Tehilla,</hi> Gr. <hi>Hymnos,</hi> Engl. <hi>Hymn</hi> or <hi>Praiſe. 3dly.</hi> Heb. <hi>Shir,</hi> Gr. <hi>Ode,</hi> Engl. <hi>Song</hi> or <hi>Lays:</hi> which three Words are found in the Titles of theſe Pſalms. And ſome do ſay they ſignify three things or kinds of Songs, <hi>viz. 1ſt.</hi> Pſalms, the Pſalms of <hi>David;</hi> others, all ſorts of ſpiritual Songs to be ſung with Muſick. <hi>2dly.</hi> Hymns for humane pre-compoſed Songs of Praiſe. And <hi>3dly.</hi> Spiritual Songs from the immediate Inſpiration of the Holy Spirit; and, as others ſay, are Songs com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed, wherein are contained all ſorts of ſpiritual Teachings. And from hence they aſſert the Singing of <hi>David</hi>'s Pſalms, and precompoſed Hymns, as well as ſpiritual Songs.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. I think it is clear from the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, that however the Words may differ the one to the other, as to the Extent of their Significations, yet they are uſed but
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:175970:32"/>for one manner of compounded Worſhip. <hi>1ſt.</hi> For though the matter of a Song is ſo confined that it cannot be externally expreſſed without a humane Voice of Words, yet the Tone or Tune may be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed either by Voice, (though never uſed in the Worſhip of God without the matter) or by muſical Inſtruments: both of which, as they were uſed according to the Inſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in the Old Teſtament-Worſhip, were Praiſes, or praiſing God; ſometimes both in matter and manner; but at other times, the matter not properly being Praiſes, it conſiſted only in the manner of Delivery; as Pſalm 17, is call'd <hi>a Prayer of</hi> David, and Pſalm 50 was <hi>a mournful Prayer when</hi> Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than <hi>came to</hi> David <hi>after he had gone in to</hi> Bathſheba; but yet it was delivered to the chief Muſician. And ſo are Songs ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times Praiſes, and ſometimes Prayers and Complainings, <hi>Pſalm</hi> 48, 120, 123, 130. And the whole Book of Pſalms, though the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of it is not all Praiſes but Prophecies, mournful Prayers and Lamentations, yet it is titled <hi>Tehillim,</hi> Hymns or Praiſes, becauſe, as all of it, whether called Pſalms, Hymns, or Songs, were after the ſame manner com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed by the infallible Inſpiration of the Holy Spirit,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 16.19. 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 29.27, 28. 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 16.5, 6. <hi>ch.</hi> 15.16, <hi>to</hi> 25.</note> ſo they were (many of them, if not all) alike delivered to the chief Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſician, and ſung by melodious Voices and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments of Muſick together; which out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Glory and Grandeur, ſuitable to that Temple-State, was to the external Honour
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:175970:32"/>and Praiſe of the moſt high God,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 29.25, 26, 30. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 4. <hi>Pſalm</hi> 6. <hi>Pſalm</hi> 48. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 120. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 123. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 130. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 145.</note> whatever the matter of thoſe Songs were. And as the matter of thoſe Songs differ (not from the Titles of them) but yet were alike com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed and delivered for Temple-Worſhip: So what ſpiritual Songs hath been, or here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after may appear in the Goſpel-Church, by the ſpecial Gift of the Holy Spirit, though the matter may ſomewhat differ (not from the Titles of them, nor as thoſe in Mourning and Lamentation) yet they were and ſhall be compoſed and delivered alike by the Holy Spirit according to Goſpel-Order.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. Thoſe three Words, <hi>Pſalms, Hymns,</hi> and <hi>ſpiritual Songs,</hi> cannot be underſtood of three different things in the New Teſtament from the different Extent of their Significa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. <hi>1ſt.</hi> Becauſe no Old-Teſtament-Names do prove the Nature of New-Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment-Things, as Circumciſion, Cenſer, In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſe, Alter, Sacrifice, Paſſover, City <hi>Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem,</hi> Temple, are all things of a different Nature in the Old-Teſtament, to what they are ſometimes uſed for in the New: So that Old-Teſtament-Names given to New-Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment-Singing, do no more prove either the matter or manner to be the ſame, nor eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſh Old-Teſtament-Singing in the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel-Church, than the other Old-Teſtament Names do thoſe Old-Teſtament-Things in Goſpel-Times. <hi>2dly.</hi> As thoſe three Words are before proved to be indifferently ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied to one and the ſame thing in the Old Teſtament; ſo there is leſs Reaſon that they
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:175970:33"/>ſhould have different Significations in the New: for you may find that ſeveral Old-Teſtament Names are given to one Goſpel-Thing;<note place="margin">1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.5. <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.21, 22. <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.29. <hi>Heb.</hi> 4.14. <hi>ch.</hi> 9.26. <hi>ch.</hi> 13.10. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.7.</note> as the Saints are called a ſpiritual Houſe and Temple, an Holy Prieſthood, and Jews; and Chriſt is called an High Prieſt, a Sacrifice, an Altar and Temple: and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it being uſual to call Goſpel-Things by divers Names of different Natures, in the Old Teſtament, there is no Reaſon that thoſe three Names, <hi>Pſalms, Hymns,</hi> and <hi>ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual Songs,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>John</hi> 2.19, 21. <hi>See</hi> Pool<hi>'s Annot on Col.</hi> 3.16.</note> which, as <hi>Pool</hi> confeſſeth, were promiſcuouſly uſed, and which are here de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrated to intend but one thing in the Old Teſtament, ſhould be underſtood of any more than of one thing or ſort of Goſpel-ſpiritual-Singing, reſpecting its Compoſure and Delivery.</p>
                     <p>Eighth Objection, <hi>It is a moral Duty for wicked Men to pray and ſing Praiſes to God, which they are not able to do without a Form; and therefore Forms are lawful.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1.<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Prov.</hi> 21.4, 27. <hi>ch.</hi> 15.8.</note> The Scriptures ſay that <hi>the plowing of the Wicked is Sin,</hi> and that <hi>the Sacrifice of the Wicked is an Abomination to the Lord:</hi> and wherefore, but becauſe what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever Good he doth, or deſireth, it is not for good Ends, to ſerve and glorify God, but to conſume his Mercies upon his Luſts; he turneth all into Sin,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Jam.</hi> 4.3.</note> and therefore all he doth is but Sin: if he prays for Grace, he doth but play the Hypocrite with God, for as he knoweth not what it is, ſo he doth not deſire it, for he loves his own Sins and Luſts
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:175970:33"/>more than Grace; and therefore his Prayers cannot be pleaſing to the Lord, whilſt he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maineth a hardned Sinner.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. All Men ought not only to pray, and praiſe God as their Creator, but to keep the whole Law in the perfect State of Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cency in which they were created in <hi>Adam;</hi> but now they have no power in themſelves to perform the inward ſpiritual Works of the Law, to love the Lord their God with all their Hearts, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and to pray, and ſing Praiſes to him; they can do neither of theſe ſincerely in their Hearts:<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.14.</note> for <hi>the Law is ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual,</hi> and requires ſpiritual Obedience; but <hi>they are carnal, ſold under Sin,</hi> and blinded in their Minds. And as they have not a true ſenſe of their Sins, nor ſee their need of Chriſt; ſo they know not that they have cauſe to ſing his Praiſe for their Being: And therefore for ſuch to uſe a Form of Prayer or Singing, when they have no Senſe nor Underſtanding of what they pray for, or that they have cauſe to ſing, is to mock God with their Lips with that which they have not in their Hearts. Beſides, the putting of Perſons on formal Worſhip, is not the way to get the Spirit, but to reſt on formal Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, which hinder their coming to Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
                     <p n="3">3. As Forms are many ways ſinful and hurtful to the Souls of Men, ſo there is no need of them, as Crutches for Lame Men, to bring them to Jeſus Chriſt; for where there is a true Conviction and ſenſe of Sins,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:175970:34"/>that Soul can cry againſt them; and if it be but with <hi>Lord, be merciful to me a Sinner,</hi> he ſhall (as Chriſt ſaith) be rather juſtified than with a formal Prayer, without Convictions: And when they are Sons, God ſendeth forth the Spirit of Adoption into their Hearts,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.6. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.15.</note> that crieth, and teacheth them, whereby they cry, Abba, Father, without the help of humane Forms.</p>
                     <p>Ninth Objection, <hi>All true Believers and ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere Chriſtians have continual cauſe to rejoice in the Lord, and magnify God in the higheſt Cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bration of his Praiſe: and therefore it is their Duty in his conſtant Worſhip to ſing his Praiſe.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Anſw.</hi> Whatever Cauſe we have to rejoice in the Lord, and to glorify God in the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Celebration of his Praiſe, for Redempti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on-Grace, and thoſe ſure and everlaſting Mercies confirmed to us in the Blood of Jeſus Chriſt, yet it doth not from thence follow that we ſhould conſtantly ſing to God in his publick Worſhip.</p>
                     <p n="1">1. Becauſe that in this Life the Joys and Conſolations of our Redemption-Grace, is mixed with Sorrows for Sins, Temptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, Troubles and Afflictions, which de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prive us of the conſtant exerciſe of the Grace of Joy in our Souls. And, as <hi>Solomon</hi> ſaith, <hi>To every thing there is a Seaſon,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 3.1, 4.</note> 
                        <hi>and a Time to every Purpoſe under the Heaven: A Time to weep, and a Time to laugh; a Time to mourn, and a Time to dance.</hi> And the Times of the Church of Chriſt are differently ſet forth,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Cant.</hi> 2.11.</note> and compared by the Holy Spirit to <hi>Winter
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:175970:34"/>and Summer; when the Flowers appear on the Earth, and the Time of the ſinging of Birds is come.</hi> And, as I ſhewed before, that the Jew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſh Church, through Sin and Unbelief, had her Wilderneſs and Tabernacle-State and Time of Trouble, which called for Mourn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and Humiliation more than Singing, ſo the Goſpel-Church hath her Wilderneſs and Sackcloth-State, in which ſhe muſt propheſy 1260 Days. Now as Sackcloth,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Iſa.</hi> 22.12.</note> which beto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kens Mourning, and Singing, are inconſiſtent with each other; ſo we ſhould not imagine that God requireth ſuch Oppoſites in Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture both together. For he hath appointed unto them that mourn in <hi>Zion, to give unto them Beauty for Aſhes,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Iſa.</hi> 61.3.</note> 
                        <hi>the Oil of Joy for Mourning, the Garment of Praiſe for the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of Heavineſs.</hi> And as the Apoſtle ſaith,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Jam.</hi> 5.13.</note> 
                        <hi>Is any among you afflicted? let him pray: Is any merry? let him ſing Pſalms.</hi> From which it is manifeſt that Affliction and Prayer, and Rejoicing and Singing, have their different Seaſons: and that until the one be taken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, the other is not given. But ſome may think that the two Sackcloth-Witneſſes in <hi>Rev.</hi> 11. are not the Church of Chriſt, but two particular Perſons and eminent Witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes that ſhould ariſe. But to me it is plain that they muſt be underſtood of the viſible Church of Chriſt: for if the three Days and an half of their lying dead, as is gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally owned, and cannot be otherwiſe under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood, be the ſpace of three Years and an half of Time; then alſo by the ſame Rule
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:175970:35"/>the 1260 Days of their propheſying in Sackcloth muſt be taken for 1260 Years, which is too long a time for one Age, or two particular Perſons to continue: And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the two Sackcloth-Witneſſes are the vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible Church of Chriſt,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Rev.</hi> 13.7.</note> which the Beaſt ſhall make War upon and overcome.<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Ch.</hi> 12.14.</note> And ſo al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo muſt the Woman in the Wilderneſs be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood of the Church of Chriſt under her Troubles and Perſecutions in the Kingdom and Patience of Jeſus Chriſt.<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Rev.</hi> 1.9.</note> For all that will live <hi>godly in Chriſt Jeſus,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.12.</note> 
                        <hi>ſhall ſuffer Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution.</hi> And we muſt <hi>thrô much Tribulation enter into the Kingdom of God.</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Acts</hi> 14.22</note> Seeing therefore <hi>it is given to us not only to believe on Chriſt, but alſo to ſuffer for his Sake;</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Phil.</hi> 1.29.</note> and that God has ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed his Church her Days of Mourning; and that thrô her falling away from her primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Love and Zeal, ſhe has loſt much of thoſe bleſſed Gifts of the Holy Spirit ſhe then had. Let us not deceive our ſelves, and think to recover the Gift of Singing with our carnal Spirits,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Iſa.</hi> 22.12, 13.</note> in an improper and contrary Seaſon, <hi>Iſrael</hi>-like, when we ſhould mourn for the great Apoſtacy, Pride, Covetouſneſs and Carnality of Spirit which is found in the Church of Chriſt, and faſt and pray for the Pardon of Sins,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Iſa.</hi> 32.15.</note> the full Deliverance of the Captive Daughter of <hi>Sion,</hi> and the Return of the Holy Spirit, that the Wilderneſs may become a fruitful Field. And therefore as our Sins deprive us, and as God hath not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lotted to us a Heaven of continual Joy and conſtant Singing in this preſent evil World;
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:175970:35"/>ſo the different Graces of his Holy Spirit, and Duties required of us, are ſuited to the different Circumſtances of our Lives, which are moſtly filled with Troubles, Sins and Temptations. And though particular Saints may and oft-times do rejoice and glory in Tribulations when the Spirit of Glory reſts upon them, and raiſes their Hearts above their Troubles; yet this is but now and then at certain Times through a ſight of Faith, when God is ſealing his Love upon their Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, to incourage their Souls to perſevere: Otherwiſe if it were conſtant, Troubles would be no more Troubles, nor Afflictions no more Afflictions; or, if their Joys were greater and more conſtant than their Sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rows, it could not ſo properly be called a Sackcloth, mournful, afflicted State; for ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of them which is moſt conſtant, and in which we have the greateſt Share and Exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe of our Lives, deſervedly beareth the Name. And therefore if particular Souls, or the Church of Chriſt in general, be in a State of Trouble and Affliction, they are ſo far uncapable of the conſtant Exerciſe of the Grace of Joy, and conſequently of conſtant ſpiritual Singing in the publick Worſhip of God, as their Troubles and Sorrows muſt needs exceed their Joys; and then the Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and Duties ſuitable to that State ſhould be in exerciſe, as Long-ſuffering, Patience, Faith of Reliance, Meekneſs, Watching, Praying, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which are more ſtrongly injoi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and oftner preſſed on us in the New
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:175970:36"/>Teſtament for our conſtant Practice, than Singing is, and that becauſe our Troubles and Sorrows are more conſtant than our ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual Raptures: So that from our Incapaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of maintaining a conſtant and ſufficient Exerciſe of the Grace of Joy in our Souls, through the Troubles, Sins and Temptations of this World, the Weakneſs of our Faith, and want of the ſufficient Gift of the Holy Spirit, we are not now able to ſing with the Spirit, and with the Underſtanding alſo, in the conſtant and publick Worſhip of God, and to preſs it beyond our Underſtanding, proportion of Faith, and meaſure of the gracious Gift of the Holy Spirit, when o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Graces ſhould be in exerciſe, is a Sin.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. Every true Chriſtian, nor the Church of Chriſt in general, is not capable to ſing Praiſes to the Lord in his publick and conſtant Worſhip; becauſe the greateſt number of Chriſtians, as it is believed, eſpecially in our Day, have not attained to a ſufficient Faith of Aſſurance of the Love of God in Chriſt Jeſus unto their Souls,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Rom</hi> 5.1 <hi>to</hi> 5.</note> (which made the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles to rejoice with Joy unſpeakable, and full of Glory) but have their doubtings be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween Hope and Fear of what ſhall become of them to all Eternity:<note place="margin">1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.8.</note> And therefore while they are in the new Birth, or Babes in Chriſt, and have not met with the witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing Power,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.15.</note> or perſwaſive Influence of the Holy Spirit with their Spirits, that they are the Children of God, they cannot ſing his Praiſe for their Redemption: for if they are
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:175970:36"/>not ſufficiently aſſured of it by Faith, they cannot ſo rejoice in it. And we ſhould not think that God requireth more of his Church and People than he hath given Ability and Qualifications to perform.</p>
                     <p>Tenth Objection, <hi>Formal Prayer and Sing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing were uſed under the Law: and therefore why not formal Prayer and Singing under the Goſpel?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Anſwer.</hi> As the viſible and ſucceſſive Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters of the Worſhip and Service of God under the Law, were not called as ſpiritual converted regenerated Believers, but were an Election out of the natural and carnal Seed of <hi>Abraham</hi> in their Generations, by Succeſſion unto the Miniſterial Office: ſo the Body of the Old-Teſtament-Church were not called into that viſible Church-State as ſpiritual regenerated Believers, but as the natural and carnal Seed of <hi>Abraham, Iſaac,</hi> and <hi>Jacob.</hi> And therefore as that People were carnally and nationally imbodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed into a viſible Church-ſtate; ſo their inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuted Worſhip was formal, literal, ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nial, carnal and typical, ſuitable to them, and the Deſign of God to make them and their Church-State a Type, Shadow and Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure of his calling a ſpiritual People into a more ſpiritual Church-State, to ſerve him in more ſpiritual Ordinances in Spirit and in Truth: And therefore ſince Chriſt is come in the Fleſh, and hath removed and aboliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Moſaical and Levitical Church-State,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Heb.</hi> 7.12, 17, 18. <hi>Chap.</hi> 9.8 <hi>to</hi> 11.</note> the New-Teſtament-Writers have deſcribed Goſpel-Things in oppoſition to them, as
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:175970:37"/>Power to Form,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.20, 29. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.11. <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.2, 3. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.6. <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.6. <hi>Chap.</hi> 1.28, 29. <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.3. <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.29. <hi>Chap.</hi> 4.21, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 29 <hi>to the End. Heb.</hi> 10.1. <hi>Chap.</hi> 9.1, 11, 23. <hi>Col.</hi> 2.17.</note> as Spirit to Fleſh, as Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual to Literal and Carnal, as ſpiritual Seed to fleſhly or carnal Seed, as Shadows to Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, as Worldly to Heavenly, as Types and Figures of good Things to come: So that there is no legal inſtituted Worſhip, as found in the publick Levitical Service and Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances, that can be either proper or a ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Warrant for our Practice in Goſpel-Times; and therefore it is our Duty to look more directly into the Goſpel-Inſtitutions for Goſpel-Worſhip, than to confuſe the Minds of weak Chriſtians with Queſtions from the dark Shadows of the Law, which tend to Bondage, and have proved very miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chievous to the Goſpel-Church; for which cauſe many, whom God hath graciouſly en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightned in the Holy Scriptures, have been forced to treat the more largely on Legal Ceremonies,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.14, 15, 17.</note> to remove the Vail of the Law, which to this day too too much remains on the Minds of many Chriſtians.</p>
                     <p>Eleventh Objection, <hi>Prayer under the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel is an Ordinance of the ſame Nature as it was under the Law; and therefore Singing under the Goſpel may alſo be of the ſame Nature, and intend the ſame thing as it did in the Legal Worſhip.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Anſwer.</hi> It is true that private Prayer is a Duty of the ſame Nature under the Goſpel as it was under the Law, both with reſpect to the like Occaſions, Wants and Neceſſities of the Saints; and to the ſame Spirit, by which all true Believers do offer up ſpiritual
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:175970:37"/>and effectual Prayers to God. But as to the Conveyance and Delivery of Prayer as an Ordinance, in and for the publick miniſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial and ordinary inſtituted Service of God in his Church, there is a Difference in Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel-Times to what it was under the Law: for ſuch publick Prayers were conveyed and delivered formerly with dark Shadows, and carnal Ordinances, by which means the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituality of ſpiritual Perſons (as <hi>David,</hi> of whom it is ſaid, that he praiſed God by the Miniſtry of the Prieſts and Levites) in the publick Worſhip of God was greatly vailed to what it now is,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 7, 6. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.13, 14, 15. 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 29.25 <hi>to</hi> 31. <hi>Nehem.</hi> 11.17, 22.</note> ſince all thoſe Forms, Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonial Shadows, and carnal Ordinances are removed: for while the Prieſts were offering the Sacrifices, the Prieſts and Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vites, in Songs with Inſtruments of Muſick, delivered ſuch Pſalms of Prayers and Praiſes as were appointed for the publick Service of God. So that publick Prayers in the ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary and conſtant Worſhip of God in the Old-Teſtament-Church, was miniſtred in a different manner to what it now is, and ought to be under the Goſpel; and therefore whatſoever Singing hath been, or ſtill may be in Goſpel-Times, may as well differ from the Old-Teſtament-Temple-Singing. But having before ſhewed that Temple-Singing was no Type of Singing in the Goſpel-Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bernacle-Church-State, there is the leſs need of any Reply to this Objection.</p>
                     <p>Twelfth Objection, <hi>Since the extraordinary Gifts of the Holy Spirit are ceaſed, we muſt
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:175970:38"/>now pray and preach by its ordinary Gifts; and if we are allowed to uſe precompoſed Forms of Preaching, why not of</hi> (they might ſay <hi>Prayer and) Singing alſo.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. I do acknowledg and aſſert that we ſhould not neglect Prayer, till we have an extraordinary Gift or Impulſe of Spirit unto Prayer; but we ſhould conſtantly go to God as we can, not only for Continuance of thoſe Mercies we have, but for further Supplies of our inward and outward Wants, which are the chiefeſt part of Prayer. But Singing proceeds from a Fulneſs of Injoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and is called a <hi>Breaking forth,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Iſa.</hi> 52.9.</note> and therefore requires a greater Meaſure of the Holy Spirit. For we can pray for what we have not, but we ſhould break forth into Singing from what we have; otherwiſe we mock God, and draw nigh unto him with our Mouths,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Iſa.</hi> 29.13.</note> and honour him with our Lips, when our Hearts are far from him; and our Fear towards him is taught by the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts of Men; and therefore when I conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the preſent State and Frame of the Churches of Jeſus Chriſt, I much wonder that ſo many ſhould be for Singing, when their Hearts are ſo much below Prayer: for if we ſhould go from Saint to Saint, we ſhould find that this is the general Cry, I have a dead and ſtony Heart, ſaith one; and another mourneth under the Strength and Power of Sins and Temptations; and a third for the Light of God's Countenance: and the great Complaint is, I am dull and
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:175970:38"/>heavy, and cannot profit in Ordinances; and that which is worſt of all, I am ſhut up in my Spirit, that I cannot pray, I want the Spirit of Prayer and Supplications. Now if thus it be, then where is the Spirit of Singing? Will you lie, and expreſs that with your Lips to God which you have not in your Hearts?</p>
                     <p>But ſome of theſe will ſay, <hi>Singing will raiſe my Spirit, I find Refreſhment by it, and therefore I am for Singing.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>To this I anſwer, That there may be a na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural ſenſual Joy in the Heart when it is not from the Light and Influence of the Holy Spirit, and therefore we muſt beware that we make not our Spirits a Standard for the Worſhip of God, but that we try our Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits by the Scriptures.</p>
                     <p n="2">
                        <hi>2dly.</hi> As to Forms of <hi>(Prayer and)</hi> Sing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, I have ſufficiently treated of them be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, and that the ſufficient Gifts of the Holy Spirit ſhall continue for the Worſhip of God in the Goſpel-Church to the end of the World; and therefore my Buſineſs here, is, only to ſhew that the uſing a Form of Preaching, is no Example for a Form of Singing: if it be, why not of Prayer alſo? which you deny, becauſe there is Reaſon for a Form of Preaching from the Word of God, and Example of Chriſt himſelf, who read a Text, and then preached from it; though as he was not, ſo others are not limited to that, or any other particular Forms; yet it is lawful for them, and required of them,
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:175970:39"/>to <hi>compare ſpiritual things with ſpiritual;</hi> to <hi>attend on Reading and Meditations,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.13. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.13, 15. 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.13. <hi>ch.</hi> 2.15. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.6.</note> 
                        <hi>and to hold faſt the Form of ſound Words, rightly dividing the Word of Truth as a Workman that needs not to be aſhamed of his Work:</hi> as <hi>Paul,</hi> who ſaith, <hi>Theſe things, Brethren, I have in a Figure tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred to my ſelf, and to</hi> Apollos <hi>for your ſakes.</hi> So that where the Scriptures do give us Liberty, we may uſe it: but it is our Sin to take it where it is forbidden; as I have ſhewed it is to uſe a Form of Prayer or Singing.</p>
                     <p>I could ſay more of the different Nature of Preaching to that of Prayer and Singing, but I think it is needleſs here, and therefore I ſhall conclude, with my humble Requeſt to all thoſe that are for Singing of <hi>David</hi>'s Pſalms, or any preſcribed Forms of Singing, as the Cuſtom is, that they would be pleaſed ſeriouſly to conſider of theſe ſeveral things following.</p>
                     <p n="1">1. That the vocal Singing together, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of <hi>David</hi>'s Pſalms, or any humane pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compoſed Forms, is a corrupting of the pure Worſhip of Jeſus Chriſt, in mingling of Law and Goſpel, or humane and divine things together.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. It will lead us to Apoſtacy, to return from whence we came, as a Dog to his Vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit, and as a Sow that is waſhed to her wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing in the Mire.</p>
                     <p n="3">3. Conſider ſeriouſly, you that are Leaders of the Lord's People, and are for ſuch for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mal Singing, Whether the ſame Arguments
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:175970:39"/>you now urge to your Fellow-Brethren will be pleadable for your Practice at the Bar of Jeſus Chriſt: you may plead them here to us, but will you not be aſhamed to own them there? The Lord give you a true Sight and Senſe of the evil Conſequences of this your Error, that you may not cauſe his People to ſin, but may yet with ſound Doctrine ſtrengthen the weak Hands, and confirm the feeble Knees, <hi>and make ſtraight Paths for your Feet,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.12, 13.</note> 
                        <hi>leſt that which is lame be turned out of the way, but let it rather be healed.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="4">
                        <hi>4thly.</hi> Conſider, that if you err from the Rule of Chriſt in offering your Praiſes to God, contrary to his own appointed Way, therein you do worſhip God in vain: and I fear it will be ſaid of you, as it was to him that offered the Thank-offering under the Law,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Levit.</hi> 7.11 <hi>to</hi> 19.</note> which was to be eaten on the firſt and ſecond Days: and if any of the Fleſh of the Sacrifice of his Peace or Thank-offering were eaten at all on the third Day, that it ſhall not be accepted, neither ſhall it be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted unto him that offereth it: it ſhall be an Abomination, and that Soul ſhall bear his Iniquity.</p>
                     <p n="5">
                        <hi>5thly</hi> and laſtly. It is the Duty of all, and of every individual Chriſtian, ſtudiouſly to judg of the Doctrine delivered to them, whether it be of Man or of God; and to conform to the Authority of the Holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; as the noble <hi>Bereans</hi> did,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Acts</hi> 17.10, 11.</note> 
                        <hi>who ſearched the Scriptures daily, whether thoſe things,</hi>
                        <pb n="50" facs="tcp:175970:40"/>preached by <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Silas, were ſo or no.</hi> And I am perſwaded that it is for want of Zeal and Love to the Truths of Chriſt, and through that ſlothful and idle Spirit attend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo many Chriſtians, that the Errors of Men do ſo prevail.</p>
                     <p>But to leave what I have ſaid, I do be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech you courteous Reader, chriſtianly to overlook that Weakneſs you may eſpy in my Delivery, and ſeriouſly to take notice not ſo much of that, as of the main of this Subject, without ſtraining my Words beyond the drift and deſign of the body of my Diſcourſe; and to conſider, that the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of the Holy Scriptures is repug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant to ſuch formal and cuſtomary Sing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing herein mentioned, and treated of, not with any Deſign to move Controverſies, or trouble others, but to prevent the Diviſions that poſſibly may ariſe amongſt our ſelves, through the Endeavours of ſome Perſons to promote this Error in our Churches. And as I hope the Lord hath engaged my Heart herein; ſo he will bleſs my poor Endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours, to ſettle the Minds of my wavering Brethren, and to prevent any farther In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>croachments of this Error, which hath been ſo generally rejected by us for many Years.</p>
                     <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </body>
            <back>
               <div type="errata">
                  <head>ERRATA.</head>
                  <p>Page 45. line 8. for <hi>formerly</hi> read <hi>formally.</hi> P. 47. near the end in Margent, add the Text <hi>Luke</hi> 4.17, &amp;c.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="publishers_advertisement">
                  <pb facs="tcp:175970:40"/>
                  <head>ADVERTISEMENT.</head>
                  <head type="sub">There is now coming forth a Book intitled, <hi>A Treatiſe of the Holy Trinunity,</hi> in two Parts: The Firſt aſſerteth the Deity of Jeſus Chriſt and the Holy Spirit, in the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity of Eſſence with God the Father. The Second, in Defence of the former, anſwereth the chiefeſt Objections made againſt this Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine. By <hi>J. M.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Chap. I.</hi> THE Caſe is briefly ſtated.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Chap. II.</hi> Sheweth that there is but one God, the Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ator and Former of all things.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Chap. III.</hi> Aſſerteth a Plurality of Divine Subſiſtences.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Chap. IV.</hi> Of the Father.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Chap. V.</hi> Proveth the Deity of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt. 1. By his Names. 2. That God in the Old Teſtament in divers Places is Chriſt in the New. 3. By ſeven par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Texts of Holy Scriptures. 4. That Chriſt pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>exiſted his Incarnation in his Divine Nature, and is no Angel incarnate, but is Coeternal with the Father. 5. His Deity is proved by his Works. And 6. By Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Worſhip given to him.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Chap. VI.</hi> Proveth the Deity of the Holy Ghoſt. 1. That he is a Perſon. 2. His Deity is aſſerted from ſeveral Texts of Scripture. 3. By his Works. 4. By Divine Worſhip given to him.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Chap. VII.</hi> Proveth the Unity of the Holy Trinity.</item>
                     <pb facs="tcp:175970:41"/>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Chap. VIII.</hi> Containeth ſome Explications of the Holy Trinunity. 1. Of the eſſential Being of God. 2. Of the Divine Perſons, the Father, the Son, and the Holy Spirit. 3. Of the Diſtinctions of the Divine Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and the Perſons, and ſome Shadows by way of Compariſon of the incomparable and inconceivable Being of God, and of the Union of Chriſt's two Natures.</item>
                  </list>
                  <list>
                     <head>PART II.</head>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Chap. I.</hi> Anſwereth Objections againſt the Scriptural Proofs of Chriſt's Deity.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Chap. II.</hi> Anſwers to Objections drawn from ſeveral Texts of Scriptures.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Chap. III.</hi> Anſwers to ſeveral Arguments againſt the Deity of Chriſt.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Chap. IV.</hi> Anſwers to ſeveral Objections againſt the Scriptures, that prove the Deity of the Holy Ghoſt.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Chap. V.</hi> Anſwers to ſome Objections drawn from di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers Scriptures to diſprove the Deity of the Holy Spirit.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Chap. VI.</hi> Anſwers to ſome Scriptures from whence our Adverſaries aſſert that the Father only is the true God. With a general Anſwer and Concluſion.</item>
                  </list>
                  <p>Price bound one Shilling.</p>
               </div>
            </back>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <body>
               <div type="appendix">
                  <pb n="1" facs="tcp:175970:41"/>
                  <head>AN APPENDIX TO THE FORMER DISCOURSE, Concerning SINGING in the Worſhip of GOD in the Goſpel-Church.</head>
                  <p>IN the former Part of my Diſcourſe on this Subject, I laid a Foundation ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the proportion of Faith which I received from the Light of the holy Scriptures, and have aſſerted ſomething of the nature, manner, and order of Singing agreeable to the Diſpenſations of the Mind and Will of God unto his People, both un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Old and New Teſtaments. And finding my ſelf concerned in the defence of the Truth of Chriſt, which ſome have erred from in their practice of formal Singing, I ſhall farther treat on this Subject for the better clearing of it from divers things that
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:175970:42"/>lie in the way of ſome Chriſtians eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in the Truth.</p>
                  <div type="section">
                     <head>SECT. I.</head>
                     <p n="1">1. I Shall premiſe, That to praiſe God, or praiſing of God, is not confined to Songs of Praiſe; but that there are other ways and manners of praiſing God, than with ſuch melodious Singing, as in <hi>Pſal.</hi> 145.10. <hi>[All thy Works ſhall praiſe thee, O Lord,] and thy Saints ſhall bleſs thee;</hi> and in <hi>Pſal.</hi> 148. throughout, the whole Creation is required to praiſe God, <hi>for he commanded, and they were created.</hi> Their very Being and Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtence, and the order of Nature, is a Praiſe to the glorious Wiſdom and Power of God. And <hi>David</hi> ſaith,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Pſal.</hi> 50.23.</note> 
                        <hi>Whoſo offereth Praiſe glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fieth me, viz.</hi> God. And as praiſing God is glorifying, honouring, and magnifying of him, ſo alſo is glorifying God, often put for the ſame as praiſing of him, which in the following Scriptures do alſo differ from that of Singing; as in <hi>Mat.</hi> 21.16. where the Children crying <hi>Hoſanna</hi> to the Son of <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid,</hi> [that is, <hi>Save now</hi>] is by Chriſt called <hi>Praiſe;</hi> and <hi>Luke</hi> 19.37. <hi>The whole Multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of the Diſciples began to rejoyce and praiſe God, — ſaying, Bleſſed be the King that cometh in the Name of the Lord: Peace in Heaven, and Glory in the Higheſt.</hi> And this <hi>praiſing</hi> God, and <hi>Glory in the Higheſt,</hi> is,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:175970:42"/>in <hi>Matthew</hi> and <hi>Mark,</hi> ſaid to be crying <hi>Hoſanna</hi> to the Son of <hi>David,</hi> Hoſanna <hi>in the higheſt.</hi> And <hi>Luke</hi> 18.43. <hi>And immediate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly he received his Sight, and followed him, glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifying God; and all the People when they ſaw it, gave Praiſe unto God.</hi> And <hi>Acts</hi> 3.8, 9. <hi>The lame Man walking and leaping, praiſed God.</hi> And alſo Thanking,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.15. chap. 9.11, to end. <hi>Phil.</hi> 4.16. chap. 1.3, 4. 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 1.2. <hi>Phil.</hi> 1.4.</note> is glorifying or praiſing God, which is by the ordinary Gift of the Spirit, always to be mixt with Prayer, as <hi>Paul</hi> did, making mention of the Saints with Thankſgiving always in every Prayer; and therefore as God is thus praiſed, glorified, and thanked, I can ſee no reaſon to confine his Praiſes to <hi>[Songs]</hi> of Praiſe only, which the Learned Dr. <hi>Owen</hi> ſtrongly oppoſes in his Expoſition of <hi>Heb.</hi> 2.12. notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding the word in the Greek that is there put for Praiſe, is <hi>Hymneſo ſe, I will hymn thee,</hi> viz. <hi>I will praiſe thee;</hi> his Words are theſe: <q>It is declared farther, (1.) What Chriſt will moreover do, <hi>He will ſing Praiſes unto God;</hi> and (2.) where he will do it, in the midſt of the Congregation: The Expreſſion of both theſe is accommo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dated unto the Declaration of <hi>God's Name,</hi> and praiſing of him in the Temple. The <hi>Singing of Hymns</hi> of Praiſe unto God in the great Congregation, was <hi>then</hi> a principal Part of his Worſhip. And in the firſt Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion, two Things are obſervable. (1.) What Chriſt undertakes to do, and that is, to praiſe God. Now this is only Exegetical of what went before: He
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:175970:43"/>would <hi>praiſe God</hi> by declaring his Name. There is no way whereby the Praiſe of God may be celebrated, like that of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claring his Grace, Goodneſs, and Love unto Men, whereby they may be won to believe and truſt in him, whence Glory redounds unto him. (2.) <hi>The Chearful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and Alacrity</hi> of the Spirit of Chriſt in this Work, he would do it as with <hi>Joy and Singing;</hi> with ſuch a frame of Heart, as was required in them, who were to ſing the Praiſes of God in the great Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly in the Temple. (3.) Where would he do this <gap reason="foreign">
                              <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                           </gap> 
                           <hi>in the midſt of the Congregation,</hi> the <hi>great Congregation,</hi> as he calls it, ver. 25. that is, the great Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies of the People in the Temple. And this was a Type of the whole Church of the Elect, under the New-Teſtament. The Lord Chriſt in his <hi>own Perſon,</hi> by <hi>his Spirit in his Apoſtles,</hi> and his Word, by all his Meſſengers unto the end of the World, ſetting forth the Love, Grace, Goodneſs, and Mercy of God in him the Mediator, ſets forth <hi>the Praiſe of God in the midſt</hi> of the Congregation. I ſhall only add (ſaith he) that whereas <hi>Singing of Hymns unto God,</hi> was an eſſential Part of the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituted Worſhip under the Old Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, to whoſe uſe theſe Expreſſions are accommodated; it is evident that the Lord Chriſt hath eminently ſet forth <hi>this Praiſe of God</hi> in his Inſtitution of Worſhip under the New-Teſtament, wherein God
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:175970:43"/>will ever be glorified and praiſed. And he farther ſaith, — That he (<hi>viz.</hi> Chriſt, no ſooner was delivered from his Suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings, but) as <hi>he lands upon the Shore</hi> from that Tempeſt wherein he was toſſed in his Paſſion, he cries out, <hi>I will declare thy Name unto my Brethren, in the midſt of the Congregation will I ſing praiſe unto thee.</hi> And thus we find that upon his Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection he did not immediately aſcend into Glory, but firſt declared the Name of God unto his Apoſtles and Diſciples; and then took order that by them it ſhould be <hi>declared</hi> and publiſhed to all the World. This was upon his Spirit, and he entred not into his <hi>glorious Reſt</hi> until he had performed it. The Words themſelves alſo do evidence it, in that Expreſſion of <hi>celebrating God's Name with Hymns,</hi> with Singing. It was a Joy of heart unto him to be engaged in this work. Singing is the frame <gap reason="foreign">
                              <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                           </gap>, <hi>James</hi> 5.13. of them that are in a glad, free, rejoycing Condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. So was the Lord Chriſt in this Work. — Moreover,<note place="margin">
                              <hi>Pſal.</hi> 258.</note> the Lord Chriſt by declaring, that he will <hi>ſet forth the Praiſe of God</hi> in the Church, manifeſts what is the duty of the Church it ſelf, namely, <hi>to praiſe God.</hi> — This is indeed the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry end of <hi>gathering the Church,</hi> and of all the Duties that are performed therein, and thereby.— This is the end of the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution of all Ordinances of Worſhip in the Church, <hi>Eph.</hi> 3.8, 9, 10. and in them
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:175970:44"/>do they ſet forth the Praiſes of God unto Men and Angels. This is the tendency of <hi>Prayer,</hi> the word of <hi>Faith,</hi> the fruit of <hi>Obedience.</hi> It is a fond Imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation which ſome have fallen upon, that God is not <hi>praiſed</hi> in the Church for the work of Redemption, unleſs it be done by Words and Hymns particularly ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſing it. All <hi>Praying,</hi> all <hi>Preaching,</hi> all Adminiſtration of Ordinances, all our Faith, all our Obedience, if ordered aright, are nothing but giving Glory to God, for his Love and Grace in Chriſt Jeſus in a due and acceptable manner.</q> So that it is mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſted from the aforeſaid Premiſes, that prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of God is not limited to Songs of Praiſe.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="section">
                     <head>SECT. II.</head>
                     <head type="sub">Of the word <hi>Hymnos,</hi> a Hymn.</head>
                     <p>THat the word <hi>Hymnos</hi> ſignifieth <hi>[Praiſe]</hi> and is of ſuch a general Signification, as that it is not to be confined only to <hi>Songs</hi> of Praiſe, is ſhewed briefly in my former Diſcourſe,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Par.</hi> 1. p. 29, 33.</note> wherein I cited <hi>Ainſworth</hi> on <hi>Pſalm</hi> 3. who tranſlates it <hi>Praiſe;</hi> and the Dutch Annotations, which do not limit it to Songs, but do alſo admit of it to ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fy <hi>ſaying Thanks</hi> to God; to which former Teſtimony, I ſhall add ſome farther Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence for the confirmation thereof.</p>
                     <pb n="7" facs="tcp:175970:44"/>
                     <p>And firſt, in <hi>Conſtantine</hi>'s Greek Lexicon, though it tells us that <hi>Hymenaeus</hi> is a Nuptial Song; and <hi>Hymnos, Hymnus, Laus Deorum,</hi> the Praiſe of the Gods, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Yet he alſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſeth <hi>hymneo, dico hymnum,</hi> I ſay an Hymn, (as well as) <hi>hymnos canto,</hi> I ſing Hymns; <hi>ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no vel dico laudes,</hi> I ſing or ſay Praiſes. <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que ſolum de Diis, ut quidam tradunt, dicitur, ſed etiam de hominibus &amp; aliis rebus:</hi> Neither is it ſpoken only of the Gods, as ſome ſay, but alſo of Men and other Things. <hi>Hymno, etiam Kateuphemiſmon pro conqueror;</hi> that is, <hi>Hymno,</hi> alſo <hi>Kateuphemiſmon,</hi> is put for <hi>conque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror,</hi> to complain; <hi>convicior,</hi> to accuſe or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach; <hi>Hymnein,</hi> for <hi>lamentari,</hi> to lament. So in the Engliſh Greek and Latin Lexicon by <hi>Andrew Symſon</hi> Miniſter, it is <hi>Hymnus, Epheſ.</hi> 5.19. <hi>Coloſſ.</hi> 3.16. a Song containing Praiſes to God: yet he alſo ſaith <hi>Hymnum cano, Hymnum dicto,</hi> to ſing an Hymn, to ſay an Hymn, <hi>Mat.</hi> 26.30. <hi>Mar.</hi> 14.26. to praiſe, to give Thanks unto God. This word (<hi>viz. Hymnus,</hi> ſaith he) ſignifieth alſo to complain, which is a more foreign Signification. And though theſe Lexicon-Writers do apply the uſe of the word to Songs of Praiſe and Nup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial Songs, yet we ſee they do alſo admit of its ſimple ſignification to praiſe without Songs. But that which chiefly concerns us, is to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider the uſe that is made of it in the Holy Scriptures. And,</p>
                     <p n="1">1. The LXXII learned Tranſlators of the Old Teſtament out of the Hebrew into the Greek Tongue, were not ſo well acquainted
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:175970:45"/>with it, as ſuch a proper limited word, to ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nify Marriage-Praiſe, or Songs of Praiſe; for if they had, then ſurely they would have uſed the word <hi>Hymnos</hi> in <hi>Pſal.</hi> 78.63. — <hi>And their Maidens were not given to Marriage:</hi> in the margent it is, <hi>Heb. praiſed; lo hullalu,</hi> ſhall not be praiſed, which the Septuagint tranſlate <hi>Epentheſan,</hi> and uſe not the word <hi>Hymnos</hi> for Marriage-Praiſe.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. In Mr. <hi>Leigh</hi>'s <hi>Critica Sacra</hi> on <hi>Matth.</hi> 26.30. <hi>Mark</hi> 14.26. <hi>Acts</hi> 16.25. <hi>Heb.</hi> 2.12. I find theſe three Authors cited, who do witneſs clearly for me, though he alſo brings two more to gloſs the matter over, and with himſelf endeavours to ballance his other Evidence in favour of our modern Tranſlators.</p>
                     <p>Firſt, it is there ſaid that <hi>Hymneo</hi> ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies <hi>laudare, gratias agere,</hi> to <hi>praiſe,</hi> to <hi>give Thanks.</hi> 2. Arabs, <hi>&amp; laudem dederunt,</hi> Mat. 26.30. and they gave Praiſe. 3. Novarinus, <hi>Quum dixiſſent laudes,</hi> when they had ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken Praiſes. 4. Interpres Euthimii, <hi>Dictis lau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dibus,</hi> having ſpoken Praiſes. He alſo ſhews us, that the Hebrew word <hi>Odah</hi> in Iſa. 25.1. is from the word <hi>Jadah,</hi> and ſignifieth Confeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and is applied ſometimes to Mans Sins, as in <hi>Joſhua</hi> 7.19. and ſometimes to God's Properties and Works, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 26.27. &amp; 107.8, 15, 21, 31. And alſo <hi>Arius Montanus</hi> tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlateth <hi>Odaeh</hi> in Latin <hi>Confitebor,</hi> that is, I will confeſs; which is in the aforeſaid Text in Greek <hi>Hymneſo,</hi> and in our Engliſh Bibles <hi>I will praiſe.</hi> And in <hi>Iſa.</hi> 12.4. in Hebrew
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:175970:45"/>
                        <hi>Hodu la Jehovah,</hi> in Greek <hi>Hymneite Kurion;</hi> by <hi>Montanus</hi> in Latin is tranſlated <hi>Confitemini Domino,</hi> in our Engliſh Bibles, <hi>Praiſe the Lord.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="3">3. There are divers Places of Scripture where the Hebrew word <hi>Tehillah,</hi> and the Greek word <hi>Hymnos,</hi> are in our Modern Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles now in uſe, tranſlated <hi>Praiſe;</hi> as Pſal. 40.3. <hi>And he hath put a new Song in my Mouth, even Praiſes unto our God;</hi> in Hebrew <hi>Shir Chadaſh,</hi> Gr. <hi>aſma kainon,</hi> a new Song; Heb. <hi>Tehillah,</hi> Gr. <hi>Hymnon,</hi> Praiſe. And <hi>Pſal.</hi> 65.1. <hi>Praiſe waiteth for thee, O God, in Sion;</hi> Heb. <hi>Tehillah,</hi> Gr. <hi>Hymnos,</hi> Praiſe. And <hi>Pſal.</hi> 71.6. <hi>My Praiſe ſhall be continually of thee;</hi> Heb. <hi>Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hillathi,</hi> Gr. <hi>Hymneſis mou,</hi> my Praiſe. And Pſal. 22.22. <hi>I will declare thy Name unto my Brethren; in the midſt of the Congregation will I praiſe thee;</hi> Heb. <hi>Ahalelaecha,</hi> Gr. <hi>Hymneſo ſe,</hi> I will praiſe thee. And Pſal. 119.171. <hi>My Lips ſhall utter Praiſe;</hi> Heb. <hi>Tehillah,</hi> Gr. <hi>Hymnon,</hi> Praiſe. And Pſal. 148.14. <hi>He alſo exalteth the Horn of his People, the Praiſe of all his Saints;</hi> Heb. <hi>Tehillah,</hi> Gr. <hi>Hymnos,</hi> the Praiſe. And in all the aforeſaid Scriptures <hi>Tremellius</hi> and <hi>Junius</hi> in their Latin Tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion render it <hi>Laus,</hi> that is, Praiſe.</p>
                     <p n="4">4. Our more ancient Engliſh Bibles bear a fuller Teſtimony to the proper Signification of the word <hi>Hymnos</hi> in divers other places, than the later modern Bibles do. In <hi>Pſal.</hi> 40.3. <hi>Tehillah</hi> and <hi>Hymnon</hi> are rendred a Thankſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giving: See the Bible printed by <hi>Thomas Ray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nolds</hi> 1549. and by <hi>Edward Whitchurch</hi> 1540, and 1541. and by <hi>Chriſtopher Barker</hi> 1585.
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:175970:46"/>and his Deputies 1591.<note place="margin">All theſe old Bibles, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept <hi>Tho. Reynold</hi>'s, are to be ſeen in <hi>Sion-Colledg, London.</hi>
                        </note> and in a Bible print<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in 1535. And in <hi>Heb.</hi> 2.12. the word <hi>Hymnos.</hi> is tranſlated <hi>Praiſe,</hi> without the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of the word <hi>ſing,</hi> according to <hi>Pſal.</hi> 22.22. where <hi>Hymneſo ſe</hi> is tranſlated, <hi>I will praiſe thee.</hi> See <hi>Tho. Raynolds, Ed. Whit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>church, Chriſ. Barker,</hi> and in his Deputies, and in the Old Bible printed 1535. and in <hi>Acts</hi> 16.25. the word <hi>Hymnos</hi> is tranſlated <hi>Laud,</hi> that is, Praiſe: <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Silas</hi> prayed and lauded God, without the addition of the word <hi>ſing.</hi> See <hi>Tho. Raynolds,</hi> the Deputies of <hi>Chriſ. Barker,</hi> and in <hi>Ed. Whitchurch</hi>'s Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and in the Old Bible printed 1535. the ſame Text is tranſlated Praiſe: And in <hi>Mat.</hi> 26.30. and <hi>Mark</hi> 14.26. it is tranſlated, <hi>And when they had ſaid Grace,</hi> that is, given Thanks (from the Latin word <hi>gratias</hi> Thanks) See <hi>Tho. Raynolds, Edw. Whitchurch,</hi> and in the Bible printed in 1535. And in <hi>Mat.</hi> 26.30. and <hi>Mark</hi> 14.26. it is tranſlated, <hi>And when they had praiſed, they went out,</hi> &amp;c. See in <hi>Chriſtoph. Barker</hi>'s and in his Deputies Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles. And by <hi>Tremellius</hi> and <hi>Junius</hi> in their Latin Tranſlation out of the Syriac Tongue, the two laſt Scriptures are rendred <hi>Laudes,</hi> that is in Engliſh, Praiſes.</p>
                     <p>Seeing therefore that there is ſuch clear and undeniable Evidence, that the word <hi>Hymnos</hi> a Hymn ſignifyeth ſimply Praiſe, we have the leſs reaſon to marvel wherefore the aforeſaid learned Doctor <hi>Owen</hi> did not limit the word to ſinging of Hymns, <hi>Heb.</hi> 2.12. For inaſmuch as he allows of Singing in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:175970:46"/>terms, omitting there to expreſs his Mind in the manner of performing of it, he would ſurely have aſſerted vocal melodious Singing from the word <hi>Hymneſo,</hi> as the moſt proper Expoſition of the Text, if its proper Signification were confined to Songs of Praiſe, and conſequently had given a far different Expoſition of thoſe words than what is clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly aſſerted by him: and therefore the Doctor by his expounding of the Text ſo indefinite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of praiſing God, he does plainly allow of the general Signification of the Word, and ſo denies its particular limitation to <hi>Songs</hi> of Praiſe. Moreover, <hi>Auguſtine Marlorate</hi> in his Catholick and Eccleſiaſtical Expoſition of the holy Goſpel after St. <hi>Matthew,</hi> gathered out of all the ſingular and approved Divines, and tranſlated out of Latin into Engliſh by <hi>Thomas Tymme</hi> Miniſter, on <hi>Matth.</hi> 26.30. ſaith, <q>It is uncertain with what words they praiſed God here, and whether they ſang this Praiſe, or ſpake it ſimply. The Greek word in this Place ſignifyeth that they gave the Praiſe due unto God, but it doth not thereupon follow that they did ſing it.</q>
                     </p>
                     <p>So that the aforeſaid Evidence clearly proves that the word <hi>Hymnos</hi> ſignifieth ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply Praiſe, which though our late Modern Engliſh Bibles in <hi>Matth.</hi> 26.30. <hi>Mark</hi> 14.26. <hi>Acts</hi> 16.25. <hi>Heb.</hi> 2.12. do read it, <hi>ſung an Hymn,</hi> and <hi>ſing Praiſe,</hi> yet there is ground to believe that their affectation to vocal ſing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing together of the metrical Pſalms of <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid,</hi> through their miſtake of the Mind of
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:175970:47"/>Chriſt concerning Singing under the New Teſtament, have overſwayed them more than the natural ſignification and particular limi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of the word it ſelf to Songs of Praiſe. For what reaſon can be given for its different and particular Signification in the New Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament, from its general Signification given by the ſame Tranſlators in the Old? And why ſhould not the ſame words <hi>Hymneſo ſe</hi> be in <hi>Heb.</hi> 2.12. tranſlated, <hi>I will praiſe thee,</hi> without the addition of the word <hi>ſing,</hi> as well as they are ſo tranſlated in <hi>Pſal.</hi> 22.22? And wherefore ſhould our later Tranſlators differ from thoſe more ancient in the New Teſtament more than in the Old? Surely it muſt be granted that the words <hi>ſung</hi> and <hi>ſing</hi> in thoſe four Scriptures, were an imprudent Addition to thoſe ſacred Texts. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore there can be no foundation nor warrant from the word <hi>Hymnos</hi> for ſuch vocal melo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious Singing at or after the Lord's Supper, ſeeing the word cannot be any proof either that Chriſt did or did not ſing at his Inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of that Ordinance: and in that, as I have premiſed, God is otherwiſe to be prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed than by vocal Singing. Moreover, if there were, as there is no proof that Chriſt did then ſing with melodious Voice, yet that could be no warrant for ſuch formal vocal Singing together as is uſed in our day: For as we ſhould not ſuppoſe but that the Practice of Chriſt therein ſhould agree with the Rule of Worſhip, whereby the Gifts of the Holy Spirit were to be appointed, otherwiſe to be
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:175970:47"/>exerciſed in his Church; ſo we ſhould ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther conclude, that becauſe Chriſt did ſing (if it could be proved, as it cannot) who had the Spirit without meaſure, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the primitive Goſpel-Churches had the ſpecial Gift of Singing, that therefore we might alſo ſing in the publick Worſhip of God, or at the Supper, after the ſame Order with a ſingle Voice, if we had the ſufficient Gift of the holy Spirit for it. But to affirm, that becauſe Chriſt did ſing at that Ordinance, if it were ſo (as it is not to be proved that he did) and becauſe that Singing was uſed in the primitive Church, therefore it is binding on us now as a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Ordinance, is to bind us to the conſtant uſe of that Gift of the Holy Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit we never had.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="section">
                     <head>SECT. III.</head>
                     <p>I Come now to diſcourſe of that which I find is made the greateſt Plea for ſuch vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Singing together; and that is, ſay they, It is commanded by Chriſt in the New Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and therefore we muſt practiſe it in the conſtant Worſhip of God. And that I may the better remove this grand Obſtacle of the Truth, as they make it, in not under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding the true Nature and Intentment of Chriſt's Command concerning Singing, I ſhall premiſe two things.</p>
                     <pb n="14" facs="tcp:175970:48"/>
                     <list>
                        <item>1. That ſuch Spiritual Singing as was uſed in the Primitive Apoſtolical Church, was from a ſpecial Gift of the Holy Spirit.</item>
                        <item>2. That the Gifts of the Holy Spirit were not given alike to every particular Member of the Church of Chriſt for publick Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip.</item>
                     </list>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Firſt,</hi> It is evident that ſuch Spiritual Sing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing as was uſed in the Primitive Apoſtolical Church was from a ſpecial Gift of the Holy Spirit.<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.22. 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 2.27. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 61.3. <hi>Eph.</hi> 1.14. <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.2.</note> For as the Grace of Joy is a Fruit of the Spirit; and as God had promiſed the [Oil] (<hi>viz.</hi> the Spirit) of Joy for Mourn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, ſo the primitive Church had ſome Ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſts of it, and did <hi>rejoice in hope of the Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of God;</hi> and through the abundance of the Spirit wherewith ſhe was baptized, her Miniſters delivered the Word of God in ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary ways and manners, <hi>viz.</hi> by Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſy, Tongues, and melodious Singing, which I ſhall here demonſtrate, was alſo a ſpecial Gift of the Holy Spirit; for after the Apoſtle had exhorted the Corinthians to covet earneſtly the beſt Gifts, and to deſire <hi>Spiritual Gifts,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.31. chap. 14 1, 13, 14, 15, 16, 17.</note> and to ſeek, that they might excel to the edifying of the Church; and that he that ſpake in an unknown Tongue, ſhould pray that he might interpret, <hi>for if</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>I pray in an unknown Tongue, my Spirit prayeth, but my <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding is unfruitful.</hi> He mentions Prayer and Singing, ſaying, <hi>What is it then? I will pray with the Spirit, and I will pray with the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding alſo: I will ſing with the Spirit, and
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:175970:48"/>I will ſing with the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding alſo. Elſe when thou ſhalt bleſs with the Spirit, how ſhall he that occupieth the room of the unlearned ſay, Amen, at thy giving of Thanks, ſeeing he un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtandeth not what thou ſayeſt?</hi> From whence I obſerve, that as the Saints of <hi>Corinth</hi> were moved by the Apoſtle to covet after the beſt Gifts; ſo it is evident, that both the Prayer and Singing here mentioned, were from the ſpecial and excellent Gifts of the Holy Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit; for as the ſtrange Tongues, and the Interpretations of them, which were then given to the Goſpel-Church, were from the extraordinary Gifts of the Spirit, ſo this Prayer and Singing with the Spirit, and with the Underſtanding alſo, being with the Inſpiration of ſtrange Tongues, and from the extraordinary Gift of Interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations of them, delivered in a known Tongue for the edifying of the Church, muſt needs be granted to be an extraordinary Gift of Prayer and Singing: For though Prayer in ſome other places may be taken as a more common Gift of Grace from the holy Spirit, and ſo might occaſion ſome ſcruple, if it were to be found joyned with Singing without any adjunct, to demonſtrate Singing to be a Gift of an higher attain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment than Prayer is; that Singing alſo was a more common Gift than is here aſſerted: yet ſeeing that it is no where in the New Teſtament ſo expreſſed and joyned with Prayer, but with a ſufficient adjunct, to ſhew that it is an higher Gift than ordinarily
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:175970:49"/>Prayer is (as <hi>James</hi> 5.13. where Affliction exerts Prayer, but ſpiritual Mirth in a ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient fulneſs of Joy from the Holy Ghoſt, puts forth Singing) and that it is here joined with a more than ordinary Gift of Prayer; there is no reaſon for ſuch a doubt, but to conclude that Singing is an extraordinary Gift of the holy Spirit. Moreover, common Reaſon tells us ſo far as it is elevated, to diſcern ſpiritual Things, that ſpiritual Sing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing is an excellent Gift of the Holy Spirit from its different manner of delivering the Word of God; for as the excellent Gifts of the Spirit that were for the miniſtring of the Word, conſiſted in an extraordinary Inſpiration of Light and Underſtanding, together with a ſufficient Power and Capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city to open and declare the wonderful Counſels and Works of God; ſo they were ſometimes farther evidenced to be ſuch ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent Gifts, in that the ſame ſort of Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip that was performed by a more ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary gift and way of Delivery, <hi>viz.</hi> Prayer, giving Thanks, and Teaching, and Admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhing, were delivered with Interpretations of Tongues, and ſome of them with melo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious Singing, which were both a Witneſs of and ſuitable to the extraordinary Gifts and Inſpirations of the holy Spirit, but not of the common Gifts: Nor doth the Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing and Thankſgiving mentioned in the following Verſes, afford an Argument to make Singing a common Gift; for as the Dutch Annotations on the word [Bleſs]
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:175970:49"/>allow that it is to be underſtood with re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect to this Gift (<hi>viz.</hi> of Singing) of the holy Spirit, being given to make publick Thankſgiving in the Church; ſo to me it is plain, that this Singing, Bleſſing, and Thankſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giving, are meant of but one and the ſame Gift, which the Apoſtle is here ſpeaking of under theſe ſeveral Names; the Nature of the two latter as having relation to the Gift of Singing, as the immediate preceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and annexed ſubject Matter treated of, are <hi>Denotives</hi> of the nature of the Song be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore-mentioned. For though we do allow and maintain that Bleſſing and Thankſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giving have relation to Prayer alſo, yet ſeeing that Singing is here laſt mentioned, and that the Apoſtle ſpeaks of giving Thanks, not ſo as any ways to intimate to us, that it is to be underſtood of ordinary Thankſgiving mixt with Prayer, but trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of the extraordinary Gifts of the holy Spirit, and of Thankſgiving as ſuch a Gift, ſaying, <hi>For thou verily giveſt thanks;</hi> and, <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, at thy giving of Thanks:</hi> by which words, relating to the Gift of Singing, and both of them, as appears in the Text, being accompanied with the extraordinary Gift of an unknown Tongue or Tongues,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>See</hi> Samu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el Clark's <hi>Annot.</hi>
                        </note> muſt be taken to denote a Thankſgiving, or a Bleſſing of God, with the extraordinary Gift of Melodious Singing.</p>
                     <p n="2">
                        <hi>2ly.</hi> In ver. 26. it is ſaid, <hi>How is it then, Brethren, when ye come together, every one of you hath a Pſalm, hath a Doctrine, hath a
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:175970:50"/>Tongue, hath a Revelation, hath an Interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation: Let all things be done to edifying.</hi> All had, or doubtleſs might have had, the Pſalms of <hi>David</hi> to read; and therefore as none can ſay, but that to have the Doctrine, and other Gifts of the holy Spirit, were ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing more than to be able to read, or make a bare recital of ſome part of the holy Scriptures: So there is the ſame reaſon to conclude, that the having a Pſalm, was ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing farther than to be able to read or ſing them out of a Book; and that as ſometimes the Doctrine as well as the Tongue, the Revelation and the Interpretation, were the ſpecial Gifts of the Spirit, ſo was the Pſalm alſo.</p>
                     <p n="3">
                        <hi>3ly.</hi> Singing, is a ſpecial Gift of the holy Spirit, becauſe it is annexed to the fillings of it as his Fruits and Effects. <hi>Eph.</hi> 5.18, 19. Be <hi>filled with the Spirit; ſpeaking to your ſelves in Pſalms, and Hymns, and ſpiritual Songs;</hi> which plainly ſhews it to be the Fruits of a more than ordinary Fulneſs and Gift of the holy Spirit.</p>
                     <p>Secondly; That the Gifts of the holy Spirit were not given alike to every Member of the Church of Chriſt for publick Worſhip, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears from 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.4, 6, 8, 9, 10, 11, 12, 28, 29, 30. <hi>Now there are diverſities of Gifts, but the ſame Spirit. And there are diverſities of Operations, but it is the ſame God, which worketh all in all. For to one is given by the Spirit, the word of Wiſdom, to another the word of Knowledg, by the ſame Spirit: To
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:175970:50"/>another Faith by the ſame Spirit: To another the Gifts of healing by the ſame Spirit: To another the working of Miracles; to another Propheſy; to another decerning of Spirits; to another divers kinds of Tongues; to another Interpretations of Tongues: But all theſe work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth that one and the ſelf-ſame Spirit, dividing to every Man ſeverally as he will,</hi> &amp;c. and <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.4, 6, 7. So that the Gifts of the holy Spirit, are ſeverally divided and diſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buted as God is graciouſly pleaſed to beſtow them for the benefit and edification of the Church; and though the Gift of Singing is not expreſly named, yet it is included in <hi>the Word of Wiſdom</hi> and Gift of <hi>Teaching,</hi> which are comprehenſive of all manner of Teaching, as well in Singing as other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe.</p>
                     <p>Having proved that ſuch ſpiritual Singing as was uſed in the Primitive A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtolical Church was from a ſpecial Gift of the holy Spirit, and that the Gifts of the Spirit were not alike diſtributed to the Members of the Goſpel-Church for publick Worſhip: From whence it follows, that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very Member, or the whole Church, as they have not the like ſpiritual Gifts, ſo they are not capable of the like ſpiritual Singing; I now come to anſwer the ſaid Objection, and to open thoſe Scriptures that are brought to prove, that Singing is commanded by Chriſt in the New Teſtament, ſo as to bind us to the conſtant uſe of it in the Goſpel-Church.</p>
                     <pb n="20" facs="tcp:175970:51"/>
                     <p n="1">
                        <hi>1ſt.</hi> Scripture that is brought to prove vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Singing commanded for conſtant Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, is 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.15,<note place="margin">See more part <hi>1.</hi> pag. <hi>8.</hi>
                        </note> 26. <hi>I will ſing with the Spirit, and I will ſing with the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding alſo. How is it then, Brethren, when ye come together, every one of you hath a Pſalm, hath a Doctrine, hath a Tongue, hath a Revela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, hath an Interpretation? Let all things be done to edifying. 1ſt.</hi> In verſe 15. there is no poſitive Command but <hi>Paul</hi>'s Example, which we ſhould follow according to the meaſure of the Gift of Chriſt which is not now attained by us for ſuch vocal ſpiritual Singing. <hi>2dly.</hi> Nor can verſe 26. be taken for a poſitive Command to ſing a Pſalm, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it is put by way of Queſtion: If they had a Pſalm, a Doctrine, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and that what Gift or Gifts of the Spirit every one of the miniſtring Brethren had, the Command was that they ſhould put them forth for the edify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Church. Nor can this Text be a poſitive Command for ſinging a Pſalm in the conſtant Worſhip of God, any more than it is a Command for the conſtant Uſe of the other extraordinary Gifts of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit together mentioned with the Pſalm: Neither is there any colour of Reaſon to think that the Pſalm ſhould be vocally ſung by all the Church together, any more than that the Doctrine, and the Revelation, and other Gifts of the Holy Spirit, ſhould be delivered or ſaid vocally together, or any of them, otherwiſe than according to the general Rule in the following Verſes.</p>
                     <pb n="21" facs="tcp:175970:51"/>
                     <p n="2">
                        <hi>2dly. Epheſ.</hi> 5.18,<note place="margin">See more part <hi>1.</hi> pag. <hi>4, 5, &amp;c.</hi>
                        </note> 19. From this Scripture I have ſhewed before that there is no warrant for vocal Singing; but that ſpeaking to your ſelves may be properly taken for in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward ſpeaking in the Heart, and have cited Mr. <hi>Pool,</hi> who renders it ſpeaking [in], which the word <hi>to,</hi> in this Text, as we read it, is there ſhewed to import. But if it were granted (as it is not) that vocal Singing was here intended, yet this Exhortation is no ſuch poſitive Command, as to make it binding for the conſtant Worſhip of God, any farther than to ſuch a Gift of the Spirit; for this Exhortation reſpects our being filled with the Spirit, and ſpeaking to your ſelves in Pſalms and Hymns and Spiritual Songs, are annexed as his Fruits and Effects; and therefore the latter cannot be attained with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the former: ſo that we are under as ſtrict a Command to be filled with the Spirit,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Col.</hi> 3.16.</note> for the inriching of us with the Word of Chriſt to dwell in us in all Wiſdom, as we are to ſing, yea, to be filled with the Spirit, being pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marily commanded (as the efficient cauſe) to Pſalms, and Hymns, and Spiritual Songs: then to be filled with the Spirit, ſhould be primarily ſought after, and inſtead of run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing into humane Forms of Worſhip, to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain the Spirit, and the Increaſe of his Graces in our Souls, we ſhould ſeek more earneſtly for the Spirit, to raiſe up our Hearts above our ordinary frames to wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip the Lord in the Beauties of Holineſs. Beſides, this Exhortation given to endeavour
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:175970:52"/>after the fillings and inrichings of the Word and Spirit, warrants none either diſorderly to improve his Gifts, or to counterfeit their Attainment of them.</p>
                     <p n="3">
                        <hi>3dly. Col.</hi> 3.16.<note place="margin">See more part <hi>1.</hi> pag. <hi>7.</hi>
                        </note> This Command, or rather this Exhortation, to teach and admoniſh one another in Pſalms, and Hymns, and ſpiritual Songs, is given neither abſolutely, to require Impoſſibilities of us, nor yet to break any other Command, nor to interfere with the order and manner of God's Worſhip, and therefore this Scripture intends no more than to ſtir up the Church of <hi>Coloſs</hi> to the At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainment of this ſpiritual Gift of Singing,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.31. <hi>Chap.</hi> 14.1. <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.11.</note> as well as of other Gifts, exhorted to covet af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter: and as the Apoſtle gives us an example by his own Endeavours to preſs after the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection of a Reſurrection-ſtate: and we are alſo as ſtrictly commanded to be perfect,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.48.</note> as our Father which is in Heaven is perfect; to walk as Chriſt walked;<note place="margin">1 <hi>John</hi> 2.6. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.15.</note> and as he which hath called us is holy, ſo to be holy in all manner of Converſation; as we are to ſing. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the nature of this Command for Singing, is no more abſolute than the others are, for our preſſing after the Perfection of Grace, and of other ſpecial Gifts of the Holy Spirit.</p>
                     <p>And if this Command be ſo abſolute and ſo univerſal, as to require the vocal Singing to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether of all the Church in the conſtant Worſhip of God, becauſe it is written in general to the Saints at <hi>Epheſus</hi> and <hi>Coloſs:</hi> Then ſurely thoſe poſitive Commands for Prayer, which are more univerſally and
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:175970:52"/>ſtrongly injoined on all Chriſtians, may be ſaid to require their vocal praying together; for we are commanded to <hi>pray always with all Prayer and Supplication in the Spirit,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 5.17. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 6.18.</note> and to <hi>pray without ceaſing.</hi> Yet ſurely you will not ſay from theſe Exhortations, becauſe they are general to the Saints of <hi>Epheſus,</hi> and to the Church of the Theſſalonians, that the whole Church muſt vocally pray together, or that Women ſhould pray at all vocally in the Church; nor is there any reaſon from the Text, or any other part of this Epiſtle, or from any other Word of God, why thoſe Exhortations for Singing, ſhould include the Women and all the Church, more than the others do for Prayer.</p>
                     <p>But ſome may object and ſay, that Pſalms, and Hymns, and Spiritual Songs, are for teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and admoniſhing of the Church, and therefore they muſt continue as part of the conſtant Worſhip of God to the end of the World. To which I reply;</p>
                     <p n="1">1. That if you will have this Argument ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viceable to prove the conſtant uſe of Pſalms and Hymns, it will be equally ſerviceable to prove the conſtant uſe of ſpiritual Songs, for all three are alike ſet forth in the Text for teaching and admoniſhing. And if you will grant that there is an abſolute neceſſity of a ſucceſſive Gift of the Holy Spirit, by his im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediate Dictates for Spiritual Songs (which ſome do, though others do not) why is there not as much reaſon to grant a neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty for the Gift of the Holy Spirit, for Pſalms
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:175970:53"/>and Hymns? For to be filled with the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, is primarily ſet forth as the Fountain of all three, which are his Fruits and Effects, and therefore there is no Reaſon to deny a neceſſity of the ſpecial Gift of the Holy Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit for any one or two of them, more than for the others; and then if all three are from a ſpecial Gift of the Holy Spirit, there is an Excluſion of humane precompoſed ſtinted Forms. But though I thus argue to clear the Truth from theſe Objections, yet I make no difference between them, as reſpecting their compoſure by the ſpecial Gift of the Spirit, ſo of their manner of Delivery in the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel-Church, for all three are alike, as hath been proved before. To which I ſhall here add:<note place="margin">See more part <hi>1.</hi> pag. <hi>35.</hi>
                        </note> That ſeeing we have three or four ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Names together of Old-Teſtament<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>things and Types, <hi>viz.</hi>
                        <note n="*" place="margin">
                           <hi>Rev.</hi> 8.1, 3, 4. There was ſilence in Heaven for half an hour, while the Angel offered up the Incenſe, with the Prayers of the Saints, alluding to the cuſtom of the Jews, <hi>Luke</hi> 1.8, 9, 10. who while the Prieſt was offering Incenſe, they made their pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate Prayers before the Lord, as appears in that it was by the whole Multitude in the outer or great Court of the Temple, where the Prieſts did never uſe to miniſter their publick Service in God's Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, but in the inner Court, called therefore the Court of the Prieſts, for which cauſe it could not be publick miniſterial Prayer. See the Dutch Annotations on theſe Scriptures, <hi>Luke</hi> 1.8, 9, 10. 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 6.36. 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 4.9. <hi>Exod.</hi> 40.26, 33. and Dr. <hi>Franois Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berts</hi> in his Key of the Bible, on <hi>Rev.</hi> 8.1. and Mr. <hi>Joſeph Mede</hi> in his Key of the Revelations, on <hi>Chap.</hi> 8.1. And the aforeſaid Dr. <hi>Roberts</hi> in Page 112, and 122. alſo ſheweth, That Pſalms, Hymns, and Songs, do anſwer the three Hebrew and Greek Words in the Titles of the Pſalms; as <hi>1ſt,</hi> 
                           <gap reason="foreign">
                              <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                           </gap> 
                           <hi>Mizmor,</hi> 
                           <gap reason="foreign">
                              <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                           </gap>, a Pſalm: <hi>Pſal.</hi> 3, 4, 5, 6, <hi>&amp;c. 2dly,</hi> 
                           <gap reason="foreign">
                              <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                           </gap> 
                           <hi>Tehillah,</hi> 
                           <gap reason="foreign">
                              <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                           </gap>, an Hymn: <hi>Pſal.</hi> 145. in which Pſalm, though the LXXII. have not <gap reason="foreign">
                              <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                           </gap>, an Hymn, but <gap reason="foreign">
                              <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                           </gap>, a Praiſe, which for ſenſe are one and the ſame, Hymn ſignifying Praiſe; yet the very word <gap reason="foreign">
                              <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                           </gap> is in Greek in the Titles of Pſalm 6, 54, 60, 66. and in the cloſe of Pſalm 71. according to the Greek, but which is <hi>Pſ.</hi> 72. according to the Hebrew, ver. 20. The Greek ſaith, <hi>Ended are Hymns of</hi> David <hi>Son of</hi> Jeſſe. <hi>3dly,</hi> 
                           <gap reason="foreign">
                              <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                           </gap> 
                           <hi>Schir,</hi> 
                           <gap reason="foreign">
                              <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                           </gap>, an Ode,—a Song: <hi>Pſal.</hi> 30, 45, 46, 65, 68, 108, &amp; 120, to 135. which account of theſe three Words, ſerves to confirm what was cited before out of <hi>Ainſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worth,</hi> Part 1. page 33.</note> Cenſer, Incenſe, the Golden Altar, and the Smoak that per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained to and accompanied the Peoples Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:175970:53"/>at the Temple, to expreſs the Antitype, <hi>viz.</hi> the Interceſſion of Jeſus Chriſt accompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nying Goſpel-Prayers. We may as well un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand Pſalms, and Hymns, and Spiritual Songs, not to intend the ſame that were pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed under the Law for Temple-Worſhip, but rather in ſuch like manner; that the word <hi>Pſalmos,</hi> which comes from another Greek Word, which ſignifies gently to beat or ſtrike, and relates to <hi>Pſalterium,</hi> a Pſaltery, a muſical Inſtrument, like a Harp; to <hi>Pſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſta,</hi> a Pſalmiſt, or a Compoſer of Songs to muſical Inſtuments; and ſignifies a Pſalm or Leſſen to be ſung to a muſical Inſtrument; doth ſet forth the ſweet Strikings or Touches of the Spirit of Chriſt upon our Souls, which produceth Melody in our Hearts, and was ſometimes vented by the Melody of the Voice: and Hymns and Spiritual Songs, the matter of Praiſe, and Doctrine exerted or put forth by one and the ſame ſpecial Gift of the holy Spirit, though expreſſed under ſo many Old Teſtament Names. But if we go
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:175970:54"/>about to limit theſe three Words, Pſalms, and Hymns, and Spiritual Songs, to their legal Uſe and Significations; we may by the ſame Rule confine the others alſo, to intend a le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gal material Cenſer, Incenſe, Golden Altar, and Smoke, and ſo bring in this legal Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony, that accompanied Prayer as well as Old-Teſtament-Singing, into the Goſpel-Church. Moreover, to underſtand thoſe Words of the legal Uſe and Signification of <hi>David</hi>'s Pſalms, Hymns, and Songs, affords a ſtrong Argument for the lawful Uſe of pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcript and ſtinted Forms of Prayer, as Dr. <hi>Roberts</hi> obſerves; ſaying, that <hi>the Scripture-Pſalms, Hymns, and Spiritual Songs, are moſt of them Prayers to God, and Praiſes of God, and ſo they are ſet Forms of ſuch Prayers and Praiſe.</hi> And if it be warrantable to ſing preſcribed and ſet-Forms of Prayer and Praiſe, it is equally lawful otherwiſe to deliver ſuch ſet-Forms of Prayers (and Praiſes Prayer-wiſe) and to ſay them as well as ſing them; and I cannot ſee it poſſible for thoſe that are for ſinging of <hi>David</hi>'s Pſalms, and yet deny the Lawfulneſs of preſcribed and precompoſed Forms of Prayer, to anſwer the Doctor's Argument, but that ſuch forms of Prayers and Praiſes muſt ſtand or fall together.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. Theſe Words <hi>teaching and admoniſhing</hi> one another in Pſalms, and Hymns, and Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Songs, are no more binding for the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant uſe of them, than teaching and admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhing by the extraordinary Gifts of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecy, Doctrine and Revelation, proves that
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:175970:54"/>ſuch Gifts ſhall continue for the conſtant Worſhip of God in the Goſpel-Church to the end of the World.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="section">
                     <head>SECT. IV.</head>
                     <p>IT is objected,<note place="margin">See more Part <hi>1.</hi> pag. <hi>36.</hi>
                        </note> 
                        <hi>That it is a Moral Duty to praiſe God, and therefore we ought to ſing his Praiſe in his conſtant Worſhip.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Anſwer.</hi> This I have ſpoken ſomewhat unto already in the former Part; but finding it is made the Refuge of ſome Perſons, who cannot maintain their Practice of formal Singing by Goſpel-Inſtitution, I ſhall take the more notice of it here: For though they do aſſert their manner of Singing, both from the Goſpel-Inſtitution, and the moral Law, (for if it be a moral Duty, it muſt be ſo by the moral Law) yet as I have plainly proved before, that there is no foundation in the New Teſtament for ſuch a Practice; ſo their flying to the moral Law ſeems virtually to confeſs the ſame; ſeeing that other Worſhip hath been maintained by them from Goſpel-Inſtitutions: and therefore they not being able to produce (that which is not, <hi>viz.</hi>) ſuch a Goſpel-Inſtitution, nor to make their Practice to appear in any example of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtolical Churches found in the New Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, I ſhall now demonſtrate how little re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief they can have from the Moral Law, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther given by <hi>Moſes,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.12 <hi>to</hi> 17.</note> or written in the Heart
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:175970:55"/>of Man by Nature, which is in ſubſtance the ſame.</p>
                     <p n="1">1. As to the Moral Law of <hi>Moſes,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Exod.</hi> 20.3, 5. <hi>Deut.</hi> 6.13. <hi>Mat.</hi> 4.10.</note> though it requires Worſhip to be given to God alone, yet the Manner of it under the Old-Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment was not alike Moral, but Ceremonial, Temporary and Changeable, according to the Revelation of the Mind and Will of God to his Goſpel-Church; otherwiſe if the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of Worſhip under the Law, were alike moral and durable as the Command it ſelf to worſhip God, we are then as firmly bound to the obſervation of that which we call, and in truth is, Moſaical and Ceremonial Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, as of the moral Command to worſhip God: But that which was Ceremonial, was no other than the peculiar manner of exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting or putting forth of that, morally com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded in the Worſhip of God during the Time and Diſpenſation of the Law.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. It is an abſurd and irrational thing for any to make the Moral Law, or Light of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture written in the Heart of Man by Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, a Rule to exert the Worſhip of God by; when nothing is more certain, than that the Law and Light of Nature is through the Fall much obliterated and corrupted, that we know not perfectly what it was in the ſtate of Innocency, or that it did ſimply of it ſelf diſcover to our firſt Parents, before they ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, the perfect manner how they ſhould worſhip God: For God by Inſtitution allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>Adam</hi> to eat of every Herb, and of the Fruit of every Tree of the Field yielding
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:175970:55"/>Seed;<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Gen.</hi> 2.16, 17, <hi>and</hi> 3.1, 2, 3, 23.</note> and by Inſtitution he commanded <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam</hi> in the ſtate of Innocency, that he ſhould not eat of the Tree of Knowledg of Good and Evil. And therefore ſeeing that <hi>Adam</hi> had a ſupernatural Revelation of the Mind and Will of God therein for his Obedience, and not unlikely for his reſting on God's Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath, otherwiſe he might have been dreſſing the Garden of <hi>Eden</hi> on that day, or tilling the Ground from whence he was taken, it not being poſſible for him to know what time had paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed before he was created, but by a ſuperna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Revelation given to him. It is rather rational to believe that he had other Inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions given to him for the manner of exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting or putting forth his Worſhip unto God; otherwiſe we muſt allow, that from his very inſtinct of Nature he knew the Mind of God, as it was in God himſelf, though unrevealed to <hi>Adam</hi> by ſupernatural Revelation; which I think will hardly be affirmed by any. And then if the pure Light of <hi>Adam</hi>'s Nature be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Fall was not ſufficient of it ſelf to diſcover the Will of God for his perfect O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience to it, why ſhould any go about to make it a Rule for the manner of exerting the Worſhip of God now when it is corrupt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and when we are ſo oppoſite in our Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures to the Law of God? As the Apoſtle ſaith,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.14 <hi>Chap.</hi> 8.7</note> 
                        <hi>The Law is Spiritual: but I am carnal, ſold under Sin.</hi> And that <hi>the natural Man cannot know the things of the Spirit of God. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the natural Mind is Enmity againſt God;</hi>
                        <note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.14</note> 
                        <hi>for it is not ſubject to the Law of God, neither
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:175970:56"/>indeed can be.</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.8.</note> 
                        <hi>So then they that are in the Fleſh, cannot pleaſe God.</hi> For though the viſible things that are ſeen, do declare the Eternal Power and Godhead, and the Law of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture binds us to worſhip God; yet as <hi>Moſes</hi> ſaid,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Exod.</hi> 10.26.</note> 
                        <hi>We know not with what we muſt ſerve the Lord, until we come thither.</hi> So the manner how, is not known by this Law, but by the Divine Revelation and Inſtitutions of God unto us, without which the Sons of Men are left to the uncertain Dictates of their own Hearts; by which, as their Practice in all A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges hath witneſſed, they have greatly varied from each other, and grofly erred from the Mind and Will of God in his Worſhip. Yea, and if Chriſtians do ſo much differ in their Apprehenſions concerning the Will of God recorded in his written Word, what Union can be expected, if inſtead of cleaving to that as our Rule of Worſhip, we ſhould ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>here to the Light of Nature, which cannot ſavingly reveal Chriſt?<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Mat.</hi> 11.27 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.11 <hi>to</hi> 15.</note> How ſhould it then reveal unto us the manner of Chriſtian Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, which is now diſcovered by Goſpel-In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutions, through which alone our moral Duty is exerted? Moreover, as Goſpel-In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutions do not deſtroy nor repugn, but ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ert and ſhew forth the moral Commands; ſo our moral Obedience to them,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.3.</note> through our weakneſs in the Fleſh, and want of Perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in them,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.6.</note> cannot be accepted of God, but as they are performed according to Goſpel-Qualifications.<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.6.</note> So that whatever may be ſaid for the Morality of praying or praiſing God,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:175970:56"/>yet if it be not done in Goſpel-manner, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to Goſpel-Inſtitutions, and in a New-Teſtament-Spirit, it is no more accepted of God, than it was under the Law to ſanctify and purify themſelves with eating of Swines Fleſh,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Iſa.</hi> 66.17.</note> and the Abomination, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And as the moral Law of <hi>Moſes,</hi> nor the Law writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten in the Heart of Man by Nature, does not diſcover the way and manner of Goſpel-Worſhip; ſo no eſſential part of ſuch Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip is meerly Moral without Inſtitution: for if it were, and on this bottom to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſed in the Goſpel-Church, then Moral Perſons, as ſuch, being only in a moral Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, and deſtitute of the ſaving Grace of Chriſt, and Goſpel-inſtituted-Qualifications for Church-Fellowſhip, muſt be admitted in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Community of the Church, and to the vocal Exerciſe of the Worſhip of God therein: For ſuch Worſhip and ſuch Perſons muſt naturally go together, and cannot be divided. So that if this moral Principle be followed in its natural Tendencies and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequences, it will lay Church-Communion common to Believers and ſuch viſible Unbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers, and indanger the Overthrow and ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Deſtruction of the Goſpel-Church, and the pure ſpiritual Worſhip of God therein; and lay a foundation for a moral Church-ſtate, for meer natural Perſons, in a meer moral and natural Spirit, to exerciſe moral and natural Worſhip unto God.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="section">
                     <pb n="32" facs="tcp:175970:57"/>
                     <head>SECT. V.</head>
                     <p>THat Women ſhould not vocally ſing in the Worſhip of God in his Church,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Par.</hi> 1. <hi>pag.</hi> 21, 22.</note> is already ſhewed in the former Part of this Treatiſe. But becauſe I find that the Truth meeteth with great difficulties to be received, though it comes with Divine Authority, I ſhall ſay ſomething farther here to this par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Head.</p>
                     <p>1 Cor. 14.34. <hi>Let your Women keep ſilence in the Churches: for it is not permitted unto them to ſpeak; but they are commanded to be under o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience, as alſo ſaith the Law.</hi> This Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, though it hath ſuch a relation to the following Verſe, as to forbid the Womens asking of any Queſtion in the Church, du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the Worſhip and Service of God there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in; yet it intends more than barely to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrain them from ſuch a ſort of ſpeaking, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe by the moral Law they are put under ſubjection to the Men.<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.16.</note> And therefore ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that the Moral Law, which Chriſt will have preſerved, as confirmed by him in his Goſpel-Church, takes away all Authority from the Woman, then ſurely ſhe muſt not teach nor admoniſh the Church of Chriſt in Pſalms, and Hymns, and ſpiritual Songs; for that is an exerciſe of Authority: The Apoſtle makes it ſo, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.11. <hi>Let the Woman learn in ſilence with all ſubjection,</hi> viz.
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:175970:57"/>Subjection in all things; and ver. 12. <hi>I ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer not a Woman to teach, nor to uſurp Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity over the Man, but to be in ſilence:</hi> So that Chriſt makes it a Uſurpation of Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority for a Woman to teach or to ſpeak, or any ways to break her ſilence in the Church. And ver. 13. Adam <hi>was firſt formed, then</hi> Eve: <hi>And</hi> Adam <hi>was not deceived, but the Woman being deceived, was in the tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſion:</hi> And therefore ſhe is not ſuffered, becauſe of her weakneſs to teach the Man, but to ſhew her Subjection by keeping ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, and therefore ſhe muſt not vocally ſing in the Church of God.</p>
                     <p>But ſome will object and ſay, That theſe Scriptures that forbid Womens teaching and ſpeaking in the Church, and that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand them to learn in ſilence, do intend only that they ſhould not be the Mouth of the Church, as in Prayer and Doctrine, to ſpeak to God for them, or from God unto them; and that in Singing, they do neither of theſe, nor teach, nor learn, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Womens vocal Singing in the Church is not forbidden.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Anſwer</hi> 1. This Objection and Expoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of theſe two Texts in favour of Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mens Singing, cannot poſſibly be the mind of Chriſt in them, becauſe it is contrary to the letter of thoſe Texts: For the Apoſtle ſaith indefinitely, that Women muſt not ſpeak nor teach in the Church, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we cannot in reaſon make an excep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion for their ſpeaking or teaching, in Sing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:175970:58"/>any more than in Prayer, or other Gifts of the holy Spirit.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. For any to aſſert that the Peoples vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Singing together, is neither for Learning, Teaching, nor Admoniſhing to one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, but that this is from the Miniſter on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by his Delivery of the Pſalm or Hymn, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> is at once to deny the uſefulneſs of their vocal Singing together, and thereby to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn their practice of it; for all things are for edifying of the Church, as the Apoſtle ſaith,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.26, 28.</note> 
                        <hi>How is it then, Brethren, when ye come together, every one of you hath a Pſalm, hath a Doctrine? —let all things be done to edifying;</hi> that is, for building and inſtruction for our profit. And we may ſee in the Gift of Tongues, that if there be no Interpreter, he muſt keep ſilence in the Church, and ſpeak to himſelf, and to God: and ſo in this caſe of Singing, if it be not for the Edification of others to ſing together, it muſt not be vocally in the Church. And in the former part of this Chapter, it is mainly urged that the Gifts of the Holy Spirit ſhould be put forth to the edifying of the Church,<note place="margin">Ver. 14, 15, 16, 17.</note> as ver. 12. <hi>Even ſo ye, foraſmuch as ye are zealous of ſpiritual Gifts, ſeek that ye may excel to the edifying of the Church. 1ſt.</hi> To pray and ſing in a known Tongue; and <hi>2ly.</hi> To deliver the Pſalm, the Doctrine, and other Gifts of the holy Spirit, by courſe or turns,<note place="margin">Ver. 27, 31.</note> 
                        <hi>one by one, that all may learn, and all may be comforted:</hi> And therefore if the vocal Singing together of the People and of
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:175970:58"/>Women, be not for the edification of the Church, it is unprofitable, and ſo is rejected by the Apoſtle. Nor can ſuch unedifying Singing that is neither for learning, teaching, nor admoniſhing one another, be that Sing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing exhorted unto in <hi>Col.</hi> 3.16. Becauſe that is for teaching and admoniſhing, which is oppoſite to this Objection, and therefore by the plain literal ſenſe of the Text, it is overthrown. And if you ſhould ſay, that ſuch vocal Singing together, is for teaching and admoniſhing to one another; then where are the Learners, if all be Teachers? and how do the Women learn in ſilence, when all do vocally ſing? for it is impoſſible to reconcile ſuch Contradictions of ſpeech, as Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men's ſpeaking, teaching, and admoniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing one another in Pſalms and Hymns, and ſpiritual Songs, vocally altogether, to their not ſpeaking nor teaching, but keeping ſilence, and learning in ſilence in the Church. Neither is there any reaſon to make the whole Church a Mouth (which is compared to a Body having many Members) as ſome would have it from <hi>Rom.</hi> 15.6. <hi>That ye may with one Mind and one Mouth glorify God:</hi> for this cannot be meant of every Member, or of the whole Church of <hi>Rome</hi> vocally to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, but of their being of one accord in Spirit, and by one Mouth, (<hi>viz.</hi> of their Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter) to glorify God the Father,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Par.</hi> 1. pag. 31.</note> like as in <hi>Acts</hi> 4.24. which is fully opened before.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Object.</hi> There hath been Women Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſſes who have propheſied in the Church,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:175970:59"/>and it is ſaid that their Sons and their Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters ſhall propheſy, and accordingly we have mention made of Womens praying and propheſying; and wherefore may they not vocally ſing as well as pray and propheſy?</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Anſw.</hi> Firſt, It is doubtleſs lawful, and the duty of Women to improve the ſeveral Graces of the holy Spirit, and that if their Hearts are raiſed by ſuch a Gift of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit in the joy of the holy Ghoſt, they may ſing as well as pray and propheſy; but none of theſe muſt be done by them in the aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly of the Church, for part of the inſtituted vocal Worſhip of God therein: For I ſee no ground to believe that any of thoſe Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men Propheteſſes ſent of God, and men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned under the Old Teſtament, did ever deliver their Prophecies to the People in a Church-miniſterial way and order; but as they were inſpired by the holy Ghoſt, and as occaſion offered, ſo they delivered the Word of God;<note place="margin">2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 34.22.</note> as the Propheteſs <hi>Huld<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </hi> did to <hi>Hilkiah,</hi> and other Meſſengers which <hi>Joſiah</hi> the King ſent unto her. And as <hi>Anna</hi> did, who though ſhe delivered her Prophecy to the People in the Temple, yet it was not as part of the inſtituted, conſtant, legal Temple-Worſhip, for that was appropria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted only to the Prieſts and Levites; but ſhe accidentally coming in at the ſame inſtant while <hi>Simeon</hi> was teſtifying of Chriſt, ſhe al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo ſpake of him unto all them that waited for Redemption in <hi>Jeruſalem.</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Luke</hi> 2.27, 28.</note>
                     </p>
                     <pb n="37" facs="tcp:175970:59"/>
                     <p n="2">2. Though there is mention made of Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men's praying and propheſying in 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.5. yet this cannot be meant of Prayer and Propheſy in the publick Worſhip and Service of God in the Goſpel-Church, for that is not lawful, as hath been ſhewed; for though they have the benefit, and may par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take, and put themſelves under all the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances and Priviledges (excepting thoſe that relate to Government) in the Church; yet Women muſt not adminiſter any pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick vocal Worſhip therein, and therefore it is ſpoken of more private Prayer and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſy out of the Church in their Families or otherwiſe, as they were ſpirited, and oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion preſented, as <hi>Aquila</hi> and <hi>Priſcilla</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded the Way of God more perfectly to <hi>Apollos, Acts</hi> 18.26. or as <hi>Elizabeth</hi> by the holy Ghoſt bleſſed <hi>Mary,</hi> or as <hi>Philip</hi>'s four Daughters who did propheſy as it is moſt probable in their Father's Houſe,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Acts</hi> 21.8.</note> or as thoſe Propheteſſes before cited under the Old Teſtament. And therefore if Womens pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and propheſying, expreſly mentioned in the Scriptures, cannot be underſtood of their vocal exerciſe in the conſtant Worſhip of God inſtituted in his Church; then ſurely there can be no reaſon given for their vocal Singing in the conſtant Service of God, when there is no ſuch mention made of it as there is of their praying and propheſying in the New Teſtament.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="section">
                     <pb n="38" facs="tcp:175970:60"/>
                     <head>SECT. VI.</head>
                     <p>AS to thoſe prophetical places in the Pſalms,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Pſal.</hi> 96.1, 2. <hi>and</hi> 100.1, 2.</note> 
                        <hi>&amp;c.</hi> of all the Earth's Singing unto the Lord, it is not worth my labour to anſwer unto them in particular, ſeeing there is ſo much in the former part of this Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe to reconcile them to the Truth in hand; and therefore I ſhall only ſay, That inaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much as the Apoſtles <hi>ſound went into all the Earth,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.18</note> 
                        <hi>and their Words unto the Ends of the World,</hi> viz. of the known World, and that there was then the Spiritual Gift of vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call Singing; thoſe Scriptures may be ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied to that primitive Goſpel-time, but their more compleat fulfilling, ſhall be in the great Sabbath, which I believe will be the ſeventh 1000 years of the World, which is that Reſt that remains to the People of God,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Heb.</hi> 4.9. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 52.9. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 96, &amp; 97, <hi>&amp;</hi> 98.</note> ſo much propheſied of throughout the Scriptures, when the whole Earth ſhall be at reſt and qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>et, and ſhall break forth into Singing.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="section">
                     <head>SECT. VII.</head>
                     <p>IF it be lawful to premeditate on the matter of Prayer, we may alſo as well premedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate on the matter of Singing; and if ſuch premeditated matter of Prayer and Singing,
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:175970:60"/>may be delivered in the Worſhip of God, and limited to thoſe premeditated Words, wherefore is it not lawful to uſe preſcribed Forms?</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Anſw.</hi> Firſt, This Argument takes that for granted, which is no wiſe to be granted, <hi>viz.</hi> that vocal Prayers: and conſequently Singing, may be limited to premeditated Words. True, it is lawful to premeditate on the matter of Prayer, for if we deny this, we cannot go to God in that Duty, with a ſenſe of our wants upon our Hearts, and that the ſame wants which we are ſenſible of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we pray, may and ought to be ſpread at the Throne of Grace in Prayer; but yet we are not to limit our ſelves in Prayer to any premeditated matter nor words before Prayer. For though our wants, or the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of Prayer, be thought on before Prayer, yea, and it may be ſent up to Heaven by in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Prayer, before we come to our vocal Duty; as we ſhould always ſtrive to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain the Workings of Grace in our Hearts, either in Prayer or Praiſes to God, or other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, for the improving of our ſelves in the Knowledg of ſpiritual things, yet we ſhould not form that premeditated matter, to tye our ſelves in thoſe very words, to expreſs our Minds no God in the Duty of vocal Prayer: for tho ſuch premeditated words may expreſs our preſent Requeſts as fitly as any others; yet to limit our ſelves to them, is a quench<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the holy Spirit, in that our Hearts are ingaged and limited to the matter of thoſe
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:175970:61"/>words only (otherwiſe our Hearts are either idle or differing from our Lips, which is Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion) whereby we are barred from any far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Inlargings on the ſame or other new matter, that may be preſented to us by the various Workings and Leadings of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of Chriſt in us, while we are praying; and therefore as we experience and own ſuch a thing as the various Workings and Lead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of the holy Spirit ſometimes in Prayer, we muſt then deny the uſe of limited Forms of Words to be lawful; for in Prayer we are ſometimes broken in Spirit, under a ſenſe of our Sins, and have our Hearts chiefly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged in humble Supplications for the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don of them; and at other times our Faith is moſt active to lay hold on the precious Promiſes, and to plead with God; and when the Spirit raiſes our Souls in a ſenſe of the Mercies and Grace of God to us in Chriſt Jeſus, and ſheddeth the Love of God abroad in our Hearts; then our Mourning is turned into Thanſgivings and Praiſes by the Spirit. Now ſuch various Workings as theſe, might not all be on the Heart in Premeditations,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.1, 2. <hi>Chap.</hi> 10.1. <hi>and Chap.</hi> 5.2, 3. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 1.15, 16, 17, 18. <hi>Chap.</hi> 3.14, 16. <hi>Phil.</hi> 1.3, 4.</note> as they may paſs on the Soul in one ſingle Duty of Prayer, as may be collected from theſe Scriptures. From whence we may ſee that the holy Apoſtle in his conſtant Prayers for thoſe Churches, had the mixture of Sorrow, and of the Grace of Joy and Thankſgiving to God.</p>
                     <p>But ſome may farther ſay, That the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of Chriſt can variouſly affect our Hearts,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:175970:61"/>and direct us to premeditate ſuch a Form of Prayer, that may ſute the different Actings of his Graces in us in Prayer; and this recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciles the uſe of a ſtinted premeditated Form, with the various Workings of the holy Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit in Prayer.</p>
                     <p>My Anſwer is, That the Spirit of Chriſt can predirect our Meditations in thoſe various things that he himſelf may help to ingage our Hearts in, in vocal Prayer, according to the ſame ſtinted Words as were premeditated in our Hearts before. But as we cannot find any warrantable Footſteps thereof in the New Teſtament; and as this is not the known way of the Spirit in Goſpel-Worſhip, ſo to aſſert that the Spirit of Chriſt does predirect and limit the Form of Prayer, ſo as to ſuit his various Actings in us while we are pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, does create theſe following Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quences. 1. That no Improvement can be made of other matter in Prayer,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Pſal.</hi> 78.41.</note> and that no other things can be expected from God in Prayer, than what our Thoughts were fixed upon before Prayer, which is a limit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and tempting of the Holy One of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> not to meet with his People as he hath pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed, <hi>thoſe who remember him in his ways;</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Iſa.</hi> 64.5. <hi>Chap.</hi> 65.24. <hi>Dan.</hi> 9.20, 21. <hi>Acts</hi> 10.30. <hi>Luke</hi> 3.21. <hi>Acts</hi> 11.6.</note> and as the Lord by the Prophet ſaith, <hi>While they are yet ſpeaking, I will hear;</hi> and as <hi>Dani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el</hi> and <hi>Cornelius</hi> while they were praying, had a Meſſage from God in anſwer to their Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers; and alſo <hi>Jeſus Praying, the Heaven was opened, and the Holy Ghoſt deſcended in a bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily Shape like a Dove upon him.</hi> Which Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:175970:62"/>do demonſtrate that God was wont of old, to meet with his People in the Duty of Prayer; and it is the daily Experience of many Chriſtians,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>James</hi> 4.8.</note> that while they are draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing nigh to God in the Duty of Prayer, God is drawing nigh to their Souls, and giving them many Tokens and freſh Aſſurances of his Love and Favour to them. 2. It is a Temptation to us to neglect Prayer, unleſs we find the matter preformed in us, fit for vocal Prayer; for if the Spirit compoſes the matter in our Premeditations for us to be ſtinted to in our verbal Prayers, then we muſt wait for thoſe Workings of the Holy Spirit in us, before we can go to Prayer; or elſe we muſt approve of our going to Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, without a premeditated ſtinted Form, and to rely on the gracious Income and Gui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of the holy Spirit, for the well-per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance of it; as the Apoſtle ſaith,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.26.</note> 
                        <hi>The Spirit alſo helpeth our Infirmities; for we know not what we ſhould pray for as we ought</hi> (that is, we have not the full Fore-knowledg of what we ſhould pray for, <hi>viz.</hi> of the matter of our Prayer) <hi>but the Spirit it ſelf maketh Interceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on for us</hi> (<hi>viz.</hi> in Prayer) <hi>with Groanings which cannot be uttered.</hi> So that the Spirit it ſelf does help our Infirmities, and ſupply our fore-Ignorance of the matter of Prayer, which we may not have a full and ſufficient knowledg of, but by the help of the holy Spirit in Prayer; and therefore Prayer muſt not be limited to premeditated Forms. 3. This ſeems to reflect on the Spirit's ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:175970:62"/>Power to form an <hi>extemporary</hi> Prayer, as though he were not able to furniſh the Soul with ſufficient matter and words to expreſs it by, immediately from his Dictates, but that he muſt firſt have time to precompoſe the matter of Prayer, and afterwards limit himſelf to it, leſt his immediate Help and Guidance of us in Prayer, ſhould not be ſo good a Compoſure for our Acceptance with God through Jeſus Chriſt, as his premedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tated ſtinted Form. And therefore ſeeing that we are not to tye our ſelves in Prayer to premeditated Forms, this Argument cannot draw in a preſcribed Form of Prayer, nor Singing, to be allowed in Goſpel-Worſhip.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="section">
                     <head>SECT. VIII.</head>
                     <p>Obj. <hi>THE ſinging of humane precompoſed ſtinted Forms of Pſalms, and Hymns, and Songs in the Church, are ſpiritual Worſhip, if their Matter be agreeable to the Word of God, and if they are ſung with Grace in our Hearts.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Anſwer.</hi> Firſt,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Par.</hi> 1. <hi>pag.</hi> 15, 16, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> &amp; <hi>pag.</hi> 43.</note> That ſuch Forms are not ſpiritual Worſhip, is proved in my former Diſcourſe; and appears from the proof I have made herein, that the primitive Goſpel-Singing was from the ſpecial Gift of the holy Spirit, and alſo from the foregoing Section: for if ſuch premeditated or preſcribed Forms are not lawful, we cannot expect that the
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:175970:63"/>Spirit ſhould own them with his actual Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence in his Graces, to make them ſpiritual Worſhip: Unto which preceding Evidence I refer the Reader: and ſhall farther add, in anſwer to the latter part of this Objection, That it is not the uſe of precompoſed Forms of ſpiritual Words, or matter ſo called, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they are ſcriptural, or agreeing to the ſenſe of the holy Scriptures, which were gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven by the Spirit, that are Spiritual Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip; becauſe a Soul that uſeth ſuch forms of Worſhip, may have Grace in his Heart. For true Spiritual Worſhip does not barely con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt of ſpiritual Words, and ſome Grace, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs they be ſpiritual Words from Grace. For if a Soul ſhould be praying or ſinging to God with ſpiritual Words, and with the habit of Grace in his Heart, and is not in ſome exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe of it together with theſe words, will you ſay that this is ſpiritual Worſhip, when it is only verbal, and the Graces of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of Chriſt, in the Heart of the Perſon, is in no degree active with them? no ſurely.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. Though we are exhorted to ſing with <hi>Grace in our Hearts,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Col.</hi> 3.16.</note> yet it is not enough bare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to ſing with Grace, but with the Grace of <hi>Melody</hi> (ſee the other Text, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 5.19.) that is, ſo to be filled with the Spirit, as that by his gracious influencing Power, not only the Matter is formed from the Word, and according to the Word of God; but that the Grace of Joy is raiſed up in our Souls to that height of Melody, as wanteth to be vented forth by the Tongue. For Singing is called
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:175970:63"/>a breaking forth;<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Jam.</hi> 5.13. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 52.9. <hi>Chap.</hi> 65.14</note> and it proceeds from the Joy of Heart, and Mirth of Spirit. And if any ſhould farther ſay, that there is as much reaſon to conclude, that no Prayer alſo is ſpiritual Prayer, if there be not a powerful Influence of the holy Spirit to form it in our Hearts: I ſhall thus anſwer; That the more or leſs our Prayers are formed and produ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced by the Influencings of the holy Spirit in us, the more or leſs our Prayers are ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual Prayers. And as we cannot deny, but that the leaſt exerciſe of true Grace in our Hearts in Prayer, gives eſſence or being to inward ſpiritual Prayer; ſo the leaſt exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe of gracious melodious Joy gives eſſence to inward ſpiritual Singing. And as we ought not vocally to pray in the publick Worſhip of God in the Church, without a ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Gift of the Spirit; ſo alſo we ought not vocally to ſing in the Church, unleſs it be by a ſufficient Gift of the Holy Spirit. And ſeeing we have not ſuch a Gift, we are not capable of vocal ſpiritual Singing. But as for Prayer, it is believed, and it is apparent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly manifeſt, that there are many Chriſtians that are in the exerciſe of the Grace of Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er for many years, that do not attain to the full aſſurance of the Love of God, in his e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal Purpoſe of their Salvation; much leſs ſo as to have the melodious Joy of the Spirit filling their Hearts with the Comfort of it. Moreover, Prayer is a lower Attainment, and therefore there is not the ſame neceſſity for an extraordinary Gift of the Spirit to
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:175970:64"/>qualify us for the exerciſe of it in the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Worſhip of God, as there is for Singing. And as there is reaſon to believe, that ſuita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to the vocal melodious Singing, and other excellent Gifts of the holy Spirit, that were in the Primitive Church, there were alſo ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary Gifts of Prayer and Supplicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, ſo as we have now only attained to the ordinary Gift of Prayer and Prophecy,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Col.</hi> 3.9, 12 <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 1.16 <hi>Phil.</hi> 4.6. <hi>Col.</hi> 4.2.</note> we have ſuitable to them the ordinary way of praiſing and thanking God, which we find were ordinarily mix'd with Prayer. And therefore with reſpect to the Eſſence of ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual Singing, yea, and of vocal Praiſes Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er-wiſe, we are in a ſuitable degree ſometimes in the true exerciſe of it, as we are of other Gifts of the Holy Spirit: And as theſe increaſe in the Church of Chriſt in their proper times, ſo may that of Singing alſo from the Eſſence of Melody in the Heart, and of vocal Praiſes Prayer-wiſe, till we come to the primitive pattern and perfection of Divine Worſhip, going from ſtrength to ſtrength, till every one appears before the Lord in the heavenly <hi>Zion.</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Pſal.</hi> 84.7.</note> But while we are in this Wilderneſs-ſtate, if we worſhip God ſincerely according to that meaſure of Grace which we have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived, it is accepted of him according to that a Man hath,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8.12.</note> and not according to that he hath not: And it is more pleaſing to God to hear our Heart-Melody without or with an ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary Voice, than to hear a melodious Voice without a ſuitable melodious ſpiritual Heart, ſomewhat like (tho not in perſonal Qualifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions)
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:175970:64"/>the <hi>Publican's</hi> Prayer, that was rather heard,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Luke</hi> 18.11 <hi>to</hi> 15.</note> than the <hi>Phariſe's</hi> ſelf-righteous thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing God. And for any to ſay, that they have the inward Melody in the uſe of outward me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lodious Forms: we may rather conclude, that it is carnal and ſenſual, inſtead of ſpiritual; and from the ſenſe and workings of Nature, rather than from the gracious actings of the holy Spirit of Chriſt. I will not ſay but that God may ſomewhat own a ſincere Soul, that hath no greater Light in his way of Worſhip. But this I dare affirm, that the more we come up to his perfect Rule, the greater our Peace and Comfort ſhall be, and that whatever Comfort a Soul may meet with in any part of Divine Worſhip, coming ſhort, or going be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond the Rule of Chriſt, it is no Seal of God's Acceptance of it as ſo performed, but it is rather a Token of his unexpreſſible conde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcending Love, in taking notice of ſuch a Soul that ſincerely loves his ways; though perhaps the Miſt of Antichriſt is not perfect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly cleared from off his Eyes. But though I confeſs a Poſſibility of a ſincere Soul meeting with ſomething of God's Preſence in ſuch an irregular way of Worſhip, and dare not preſume to limit the free Grace of God; yet there is little reaſon to expect any comfort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Preſence of God in ſuch a way, for the holy Scriptures run contrary to it. <hi>Thou meeteſt him that rejoiceth, and worketh Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs, thoſe that remember thee in thy ways:</hi> not in our ways, but in God's ways we may expect to meet with his bleſſed Preſence. And
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:175970:65"/>therefore as ſuch humane preſtinted Form are oppoſite to the preſcribed Ways of God and are a bar to the free exerciſe of the Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of the Holy Spirit in us, there is reaſon to fear, that the inward Joy (tho of a ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere Chriſtian) in the uſe of outward melo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious Forms, is not from the Fountain of the Holy Spirit. And herein I humbly conceive the Miſtake lies, that ſuch a Soul being ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what affected with ſpiritual things, and the vocal Melody pleaſing the ſenſual Appetite, and raiſing a natural Joy in the Heart; then becauſe there is ſomething ſpiritual, it is all counted ſpiritual, not conſidering that as we have two Natures, ſo the workings of each of them may meet together; as in <hi>James</hi> and <hi>John,</hi> who had doubtleſs a true ſpiritual Zeal for Chriſt, which their natural Paſſion fell in with to a ſinful Revenge againſt thoſe <hi>Samari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tans</hi> that ſlighted their Lord and Maſter: But Chriſt <hi>rebuked</hi> them, and ſaid, <hi>Ye know not what manner of Spirit ye are of.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>And now, Chriſtian Reader, I renew my Requeſt unto you in the cloſe of my former Part: And if my labour herein hath been any ways helpful to you for your eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in the Truth, render to God the Father of Lights, and giver of every good Gift, the Glory and Praiſe, to whom alone it is due. <hi>Amen.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
      </group>
   </text>
</TEI>
